<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Quantum Field Theory | Grad Math@USF</title>
    <link>/tag/quantum-field-theory/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tag/quantum-field-theory/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Quantum Field Theory</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 10:53:52 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu52d4978bb57ec1511a90a19194ce34ae_631017_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Quantum Field Theory</title>
      <link>/tag/quantum-field-theory/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introductory Lectures on Quantum Field Theory</title>
      <link>/talk/quantumfieldtheory/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 10:53:52 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/quantumfieldtheory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Introductory Lectures on Quantum Field Theory&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Razvan Teodorescu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, February 4th, 2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: Quantum field theory (QFT) is the mathematical formulation of our current theoretical description of nature&amp;rsquo;s fundamental laws. It relates deeply to functional analysis, operator theory, Lie groups representation theory, and PDE, and is known for open problems such as the 4D Yang-Mills Millenium problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation will introduce the main elements of QFT by reviewing Einstein&amp;rsquo;s postulates of special relativity, irreducible representations of the Poincare group, the Pauli-Lubanski theorem and classification of free fields, Emmy Noether&amp;rsquo;s theorem, internal symmetry groups, minimal connections and gauge theory, leading to the derivation of the action functionals for electro-weak and QCD theories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The continuation would require a detour through Gaussian random field theory and the Feynman-Kac theorem, before returning via Wick calculus to QFT, &amp;rsquo;t Hooft-Veltman dimensional regularization, the Migdal-Kadanoffrenormalization (semi)group and Feynman diagrammatic expansions for standard applications such as the Lamb precession, CPT theorem, asymptotic freedom and the Goldstone-Higgs theorem.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
