<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nathan Hayford | Grad Math@USF</title>
    <link>/author/nathan-hayford/</link>
      <atom:link href="/author/nathan-hayford/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Nathan Hayford</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 13:50:43 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu52d4978bb57ec1511a90a19194ce34ae_631017_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Nathan Hayford</title>
      <link>/author/nathan-hayford/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Methods of nonlinear equations in the theory of algebraic geometry</title>
      <link>/talk/riemann-schottky-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 13:50:43 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/riemann-schottky-problem/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/asVgNLcnAz0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Methods of nonlinear equations in the theory of algebraic geometry&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Nathan Hayford&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/time&lt;/strong&gt;: Wednesday, February 17th, 3:00pm-4:00pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;:
The Riemann-Schottky problem, in modern language, asks for a characterization of Jacobian varieties of among abelian varieties. From Riemann’s point of view, the question was to address the discrepancy between the 3g-3-dimensional space of moduli for compact Riemann surfaces of genus g from the g(g+1)/2-dimensional space of Siegel matrices, in which the space of Riemann surfaces embeds, via the period matrix. The problem remained open for almost a millennium. The first hint of a solution to this problem was found (somewhat surprisingly) by I. Krichever (1977), when he showed (more or less) that the period matrix for a Riemann surface could be used to construct tau functions for the KP hierarchy. S. Novikov conjectured that the converse also held, thus answering the Riemann-Schottky problem a la methods of integrable systems. This turned out to indeed be the case, with a proof from T. Shiota (1986) shortly thereafter. In this talk, I will attempt to fill in some of the details of this story, and explain some of the consequences of this theorem, both in integrable systems and algebraic geometry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link to the Zoom meeting:  &lt;a href=&#34;https://zoom.us/j/96802432385&#34;&gt;https://zoom.us/j/96802432385&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part II link: &lt;a href=&#34;https://zoom.us/s/97923273524&#34;&gt;https://zoom.us/s/97923273524&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
