<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Grad Math@USF</title>
    <link>/</link>
      <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Grad Math@USF</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 08:52:06 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu52d4978bb57ec1511a90a19194ce34ae_631017_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Grad Math@USF</title>
      <link>/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Numerical integration in Hamiltonian Monte Carlo</title>
      <link>/talk/hamiltonianmontecarlo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Mar 2023 08:52:06 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/hamiltonianmontecarlo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Numerical integration in Hamiltonian Monte Carlo&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Lorenzo Nagar (Basque Center for Applied Mathematics)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time/Location&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, March 24th, at 1:00pm, CMC 109&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: Hamiltonian Monte Carlo (HMC) has been widely recognized as a powerful
tool for sampling in molecular simulation and Bayesian Statistics. HMC
combines a deterministic proposal - using Hamiltonian dynamics - with
stochastic Monte Carlo in order to generate correlated samples from a target
distribution. The accuracy of numerical integration of the Hamiltonian equations
of motions affects the acceptance rate of Monte Carlo trials, and thus
is crucial for performance of HMC. In this talk, after giving a brief overview
on multi-stage splitting integration schemes used in the HMC context, we
present a novel Adaptive Integration Approach (we call it s-AIA) that detects
the optimal multi-stage integrator in terms of the best conservation
of energy for harmonic forces, being able to achieve a competitive sampling
efficiency in HMC Bayesian inference applications.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Idempotents in a quandle ring and its applications</title>
      <link>/talk/idempotentquandledipali/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2023 08:51:19 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/idempotentquandledipali/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Idempotents in a quandle ring and its applications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Dipali Swain&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time/Location&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, March 3rd at 1:00pm, CMC 109&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: For a quandle, its associated quandle ring is a very interesting structure. Unlike Groups, Quandle is a non-associative algebra, binary operation of which imitates the three Reidemeister Moves found in Knot theory. When we associate a ring to such an algebraic structure, the most naturally occurring object is an idempotent. We study this object and investigate if such a collection of objects itself forms a quandle and hence try to create an invariance of knots/links. In this talk, I will give a brief introduction of quandles and an associated quandle ring. I will also talk about some popular knot invariants that arise from this particular structure.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UCF/USF special workshop on Complex Analytic Methods with Applications in Orthogonal Polynomials, Integrable Systems, and Random Matrix Theory</title>
      <link>/posts/ucf-usf-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2023 21:05:13 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/posts/ucf-usf-2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flyer&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/UCFUSF2023.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page01&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Program&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;/js/pdf-js/build/pdf.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
 &lt;style&gt;
 #the-canvas {
   border: 1px solid black;
   direction: ltr;
   width: 100%;
   height: auto;
 }
 #paginator{
     text-align: center;
     margin-bottom: 10px;
 }
 &lt;/style&gt;
 
 &lt;div id=&#34;paginator&#34;&gt;
     &lt;button id=&#34;prev&#34;&gt;Previous&lt;/button&gt;
     &lt;button id=&#34;next&#34;&gt;Next&lt;/button&gt;
     &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;
     &lt;span&gt;Page: &lt;span id=&#34;page_num&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; / &lt;span id=&#34;page_count&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 &lt;div id=&#34;embed-pdf-container&#34;&gt;
     &lt;canvas id=&#34;the-canvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
 
 &lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
 window.onload = function() {
 
 
 
 var url = &#34;\/pdf\/UCF_USF_2023.pdf&#34;;
 
 
 var pdfjsLib = window[&#39;pdfjs-dist/build/pdf&#39;];
 
 
 pdfjsLib.GlobalWorkerOptions.workerSrc = &#39;/js/pdf-js/build/pdf.worker.js&#39;;
 
 
 var pdfDoc = null,
     pageNum = 1,
     pageRendering = false,
     pageNumPending = null,
     scale = 3,
     canvas = document.getElementById(&#39;the-canvas&#39;),
     ctx = canvas.getContext(&#39;2d&#39;);
 
 
 
 function renderPage(num) {
   pageRendering = true;
   
   pdfDoc.getPage(num).then(function(page) {
     var viewport = page.getViewport({scale: scale});
     canvas.height = viewport.height;
     canvas.width = viewport.width;
 
     
     var renderContext = {
       canvasContext: ctx,
       viewport: viewport
     };
     var renderTask = page.render(renderContext);
 
     
     renderTask.promise.then(function() {
       pageRendering = false;
       if (pageNumPending !== null) {
         
         renderPage(pageNumPending);
         pageNumPending = null;
       }
     });
   });
 
   
   document.getElementById(&#39;page_num&#39;).textContent = num;
 }
 
 
 
 function queueRenderPage(num) {
   if (pageRendering) {
     pageNumPending = num;
   } else {
     renderPage(num);
   }
 }
 
 
 
 function onPrevPage() {
   if (pageNum &lt;= 1) {
     return;
   }
   pageNum--;
   queueRenderPage(pageNum);
 }
 document.getElementById(&#39;prev&#39;).addEventListener(&#39;click&#39;, onPrevPage);
 
 
 
 function onNextPage() {
   if (pageNum &gt;= pdfDoc.numPages) {
     return;
   }
   pageNum++;
   queueRenderPage(pageNum);
 }
 document.getElementById(&#39;next&#39;).addEventListener(&#39;click&#39;, onNextPage);
 
 
 
 pdfjsLib.getDocument(url).promise.then(function(pdfDoc_) {
   pdfDoc = pdfDoc_;
   document.getElementById(&#39;page_count&#39;).textContent = pdfDoc.numPages;
 
   
   renderPage(pageNum);
 });
 }
 
 &lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;saturday-1240-pm-recent-developments-in-spectral-theory-of-soliton-gases-for-integrable-equations-alex-tovbis-ucf&#34;&gt;Saturday, 12:40 pm. Recent developments in spectral theory of soliton gases for integrable equations (Alex Tovbis, UCF).&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TBA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;saturday-130-pm-non-generic-focusing-of-the-semiclassical-nonlinear-schrödinger-equation-robert-jenkins-ucf&#34;&gt;Saturday, 1:30 pm. Non-generic focusing of the semiclassical nonlinear Schrödinger equation (Robert Jenkins, UCF).&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TBA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;saturday-220-pm-nonlocal-integrable-equations-and-their-riemann-hilbert-problems-wen-xiu-ma-usf&#34;&gt;Saturday, 2:20 pm. Nonlocal integrable equations and their Riemann-Hilbert Problems (Wen-Xiu Ma, USF).&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will talk about how to construct nonlocal integrable equations through group reductions of matrix spectral problems. The reduced matrix spectral problems are used to formulate a kind of Riemann-Hilbert problems, whose reflectionless cases generate soliton solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;saturday-340-pm-sle-or-sturm-liouville-entropy-razvan-teodorescu-usf&#34;&gt;Saturday, 3:40 pm. SLE, Or Sturm-Liouville Entropy (Razvan Teodorescu, USF).&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which integral equations of Fredholm type are compatible with
the classical Bethe Ansatz? Does two-dimensional integrability giving rise to
the “Hofstadter butterfly” imply the existence of a one-parameter group of 1D
integrable models? And will we ever run out of new meanings for SLE? These
questions and others besides will be discussed in the context of the concept of
averaging of solutions for Sturm-Liouville problems on the real line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;saturday-430-pm-criticalities-in-random-normal-matrices-seung-yeop-lee-usf&#34;&gt;Saturday, 4:30 pm. Criticalities in Random Normal Matrices (Seung-Yeop Lee, USF).&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the universalities in criticality are well-studied for General Unitary Ensemble, the analogous study for Normal
Matrix almost does not exist.  I will show a specific model with a merging singularity where the critical behavior of
the kernel could be observed.  It showcases the Painleve II as in the  merging singularity in One matrix model.  This is
a joint work with Meng Yang.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sunday-900-am-nonlinear-damped-spatially-periodic-breathers-and-the-emergence-of-soliton-like-rogue-waves-constance-schober-ucf&#34;&gt;Sunday, 9:00 am. Nonlinear damped spatially periodic breathers and the emergence of soliton-like rogue waves (Constance Schober, UCF).&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TBA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sunday-950-am-non-standard-green-energy-problems-in-the-complex-plane-abey-lopez-garcia-ucf&#34;&gt;Sunday, 9:50 am. Non-standard Green energy problems in the complex plane (Abey Lopez-Garcia, UCF).&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We consider several non-standard discrete and continuous Green energy problems in the complex plane and study the asymptotic relations between their solutions. In the discrete setting, we consider two problems; one with variable particle positions (within a given compact set) and variable particle masses, the other one with variable masses but prescribed positions. The mass of a particle is allowed to take any value in the range [0,R], where R  is a fixed parameter in the problem. The corresponding continuous energy problems are defined on the space of positive measures with mass at most R and supported on the given compact set, with an additional upper constraint that appears as a consequence of the prescribed positions condition. We prove that the equilibrium constant and equilibrium measure vary continuously as functions of the parameter  (the latter in the weak-star topology). In the unconstrained energy problem we present a greedy algorithm that converges to the equilibrium constant and equilibrium measure. This is a joint work with Alex Tovbis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sunday-1040-am-it-is-useful-to-solve-extremal-problems---almost-i-newton-dmitry-khavinson-usf&#34;&gt;Sunday, 10:40 am. &amp;ldquo;It is useful to solve extremal problems&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash;Almost I. Newton (Dmitry Khavinson, USF).&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone one knows how useful the Schwarz Lemma is. ( Not really due to H.A. Schwarz.)
But what if we replace the origin by interpolating at several points? What if we switch from bounded functions to Hardy or Bergman spaces functions? What if we replace the disk by a general domain, or a Riemann surface? What if instead of analytic functions we investigate the Schwarz lemma versions for harmonic functions in R^n ?  Or, for analytic functions, in C^n? What if we move from linear to nonlinear problems, e.g. , Schwarz&amp;rsquo; lemma for nonvanishishing functions? Some of these questions have been at least partially solved, having moved analysis in substantial ways forward. And some are waiting for a new trick, new high ground, new minds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sunday-100-pm-arc-length-null-quadrature-domains-erik-lundberg-fau&#34;&gt;Sunday, 1:00 pm. Arc length null quadrature domains (Erik Lundberg, FAU).&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A planar domain is referred to as an arclength null quadrature domain if integrals of analytic functions with respect to arclength along the boundary always vanish. We discuss recent progress on the classification problem for arclength null quadrature domains, and we explain how conformal mappings can be used to construct explicit examples.  Time permitting, we will also review some exactly solvable problems in fluid dynamics where various types of quadrature domains appear as solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sunday-150-pm-hermite-pade-approximation-equilibrium-problems-and-riemann-surfaces-evguenii-rakhmanov-usf&#34;&gt;Sunday, 1:50 pm. Hermite-Pade approximation, equilibrium problems and Riemann surfaces (Evguenii Rakhmanov, USF).&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classical Stahl&amp;rsquo;s theorem describes convergence of diagonal Pade approximants for
functions with branch points. Possible generalizations of this theorem for the case of
Hermite-Pade approximations attract common attention but the progress is slow. A few
particular results in this direction are obtained by di erent authors but a general case is
essentially wide open. It is not even clear how a general conjecture on convergence may
be formulated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We plan to discuss this questions in some details. There are two known approaches
to the problem. A conjecture on convergence may be stated in terms of an equilibrium
problem for a logarithmic potential. An alternative way is to use so-called G-function
on an algebraic Riemann surface associated with the problem at hand. Either way meet
certain challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sunday-240-pm-the-ising-model-coupled-to-2d-gravity-nathan-hayford-usf&#34;&gt;Sunday, 2:40 pm. The Ising Model Coupled to 2D Gravity (Nathan Hayford, USF).&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most celebrated exactly solvable models in statistical mechanics is the two-dimensional Ising model. The original model, introduced in the 1920s, has a rich mathematical structure. It thus came as a pleasant surprise when physicists studying matrix models of 2D gravity found that, coupled to quantum gravity, the planar Ising model still had an elegant solution. The methods used by V. Kazakov and his collaborators involved the method of orthogonal polynomials. However, these methods were formal, and no direct analytic derivation of the phase transition has been described in the literature since the original paper of V. Kazakov in 1986. In this talk, we present a rigorous proof of Kazakov’s results, using steepest descent analysis for biorthogonal polynomials. We are able to calculate the genus 0 partition function, and we also find that the phase transition is described by the string equation of a 3rd order reduction of the KP hierarchy, in agreement with the predictions of G. Moore, M. Douglas, and their collaborators. This is joint work with Maurice Duits and Seung-Yeop Lee.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Ramsey Number, and Some Elementary Yet Beautiful Examples</title>
      <link>/talk/ramseytheoryboyoon/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2023 15:42:09 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/ramseytheoryboyoon/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Introduction to Ramsey Number, and Some Elementary Yet Beautiful Examples&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Boyoon Lee&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time/Location&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, February 24th, at 1:00pm, CMC 109&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;:
Ramsey theory can be roughly understood to be the statement on the existence of regular structure in a seemingly chaotic environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this talk designed for people who have little to no experience in Ramsey theory,  we will go over what the Ramsey number is, how hard it is to track down any of them while the question of finding one seems quite unassuming/innocuous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will warm up with a very easy case of a particular Ramsey number r(3,3)=6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, we will borrow a pure genius argument of L. Lovász to reach the conclusion of Ramsey number r(3,3,3)=17 and be amazed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meaning of r(a, b, c, ..) is going to be given at the talk.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Designs, Nibbles, and Approximate Structures</title>
      <link>/talk/nibbleseion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2023 09:09:11 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/nibbleseion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Designs, Nibbles, and Approximate Structures&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Eion Mulrenin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time/Location&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, February 10th, at 1:00pm, CMC 109&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: For integers $1 &amp;lt; t &amp;lt; k &amp;lt; n$ and a positive integer $\lambda$, a family $F$ of $k$-subsets (sets of size $k$) of
{$1,&amp;hellip;,n$} is called a $t-(n,k,\lambda)$ design provided that every $t$-subset of {$1,&amp;hellip;,n$} is contained in precisely
$\lambda$
sets in the family $F$. A simple double counting argument gives necessary divisibility conditions for the existence of
$t-(n,k,\lambda)$ designs, and it was asked c. 1850 (the so-called &amp;ldquo;existence conjecture&amp;rdquo;) whether these were also
sufficient. In 1963, P. Erdos and H. Hanani conjectured the asymptotic existence of &amp;ldquo;approximate designs&amp;rdquo; for
$\lambda=1$
and $k$ and $t$ fixed. The conjecture was verified in 1985 by V. Rodl, and in his solution, he introduced his seminal &amp;ldquo;nibble&amp;rdquo; technique, which has since become a powerful tool in extremal combinatorics. The existence conjecture was ultimately verified in 2014 by P. Keevash and in 2016 by D. Kuhn et al., with both proofs making copious use of nibble techniques. In this talk, we will introduce and prove some basic facts about combinatorial designs and sketch a proof of the Erdos-Hanani conjecture using nibble methods.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It’s Raining Coding Theory</title>
      <link>/talk/permutationcodespanith/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 09:03:56 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/permutationcodespanith/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: It’s Raining Coding Theory&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;:  Panith Thiruvenkatasamy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time/Location&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, February 3rd, 1-2pm, CMC 109&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: I’m planning to discuss Dr. Giacomo Micheli’s and Dr. Alessandro Neri’s paper titled “New Lower Bounds for Permutation Codes using Linear Block Codes”. We will be discussing in brief the main theorems in the paper and the proofs for those theorems, and I plan to end the talk by mentioning some questions to ponder upon that were inspired by the paper.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Introduction to Tamo-Barg Codes</title>
      <link>/talk/tamobarg/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 13:53:52 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/tamobarg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: An Introduction to Tamo-Barg Codes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speakers&lt;/strong&gt;: Clifton Garrison, Logan Nott, and Phillip Waitkevich&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time/Location&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, January 20th at 1:00pm, CMC 109&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;:  Prior to the discovery of Tamo-Barg codes, it was common for codes to recover a single erased coordinate by using all the other coordinates. In 2013, Itzhak Tamo and Alexander Barg created an optimal locally recoverable code, which is a code that can recover a single erasure using at most r other coordinates instead of all the other coordinates. This talk will introduce coding theory and the construction of Tamo-Barg Codes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Discrete Painlevé Equations and Orthogonal Polynomials</title>
      <link>/talk/discretepainleve/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2022 09:11:52 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/discretepainleve/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Discrete Painlevé Equations and Orthogonal Polynomials&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Professor Anton Dzhamay (University of Northern Colorado)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time/Location&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, November 4th at 12:00 pm, NES 102&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;:  Over the last decade it became clear that discrete Painlevé
equations appear in a wide range of interesting applications. Thus, the question of
recognizing a certain non-autonomous recurrence as a discrete Painlevé equation and
understanding its position in Sakai’s classification scheme, recognizing whether it
is equivalent to some known (model) example, and especially finding an explicit
change of coordinates transforming it to such example, becomes one of the central
ones. Fortunately, Sakai’s geometric theory provides an almost algorithmic procedure
of answering this question. In this work we illustrate this procedure by considering
two examples. The first example comes from the theory of discrete orthogonal polynomials.
There are many connections between orthogonal polynomials and Painlevé equations,
both differential and discrete. In particular, often the coefficients of three-term recurrence
relations for orthogonal polynomials can be expressed in terms of solutions of some
discrete Painlevé equation. In this example we study orthogonal polynomials with
general hypergeometric weight and show that their recurrence coefficients satisfy,
after some change of variables, the standard discrete Painlevé-V equation. We also
provide an explicit change of variables transforming this equation to the standard
form. This is joint work with Galina Filipuk (University of Warsaw, Poland) and
Alexander Stokes (University College, London, UK). The second example is also
related to the theory of orthogonal polynomials but the motivation comes from the
Probability Theory. We consider the problem of tiling a hexagon by lozenges with
some generalized weight and are interested in computing important statistical properties
of this model called the gap probabilities. This model can be related to a q-Racah
discrete orthogonal polynomial ensemble, and this computation is again done with the help
of discrete Painlevé equation. This is a joint work with Alisa Knizel (Columbia University).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Around a Theorem of Pólya</title>
      <link>/talk/polyatheorem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2022 21:42:49 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/polyatheorem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Around a Theorem of Pólya&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Louis Arenas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time/Location&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, October 21st and 28th at 12:00pm, NES 102&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: Random walks have cemented themselves as relevant objects of study in modeling diverse phenomenon ranging
from Brownian motion to the prediction of European stock options through Black-Scholes. In a paper published in 1921 by
George Polya, he investigates walks on $\mathbb{Z}^d$ and asks when the walks are recurrent or transient. Meaning if
there&amp;rsquo;s probability 1 of picking a random walk which returns to the origin after finitely many steps. In this talk we
present a recent (published in 2014) paper by Jonothan Novak which proves Pólya&amp;rsquo;s theorem using tools that a $19^{th}$
century Mathematician would recognize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Novak&amp;rsquo;s proof is beautiful in its own right, our motivation will be to
extend his proof techniques to a non-commutative setting. Specifically, we pose the problem of recurrence of random
walks on the Cayley graph of the free group generated by d letters, $F_d$. Random walks on non-commutative groups were of interest to people like Harry Kesten who under guidance of his advisor Mark Kac wanted criteria of amenability of finitely generated groups. Kesten would go on to formulate a criterion of amenability in his 1958 Ph.D. thesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our focus will be to motivate the tools of free probability theory to answer the question of recurrence on $F_d$.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Introduction to Sub-Riemannian Geometry</title>
      <link>/talk/subriemannian/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 09:20:48 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/subriemannian/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: An Introduction to Sub-Riemannian Geometry&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Professor Thomas Bieske&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time/Location&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, October 7th, at 12:00pm, NES 102&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: Motivated by real-world activities, we will explore spaces where motion in one or more directions is
restricted. Such spaces, called sub-Riemannian spaces, possess a geometry that behaves quite differently from
traditional Euclidean $\mathbb{R}^n$. Our goal is to understand the interplay between this geometry and properties of solutions to partial differential equations. This talk will be accessible to advanced undergraduate students.  Note: We will also use this talk to deconstruct the concept of a colloquium talk.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Introduction to Noncommutative Geometry</title>
      <link>/talk/noncommutativegeometry/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2022 14:32:15 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/noncommutativegeometry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: An Introduction to Noncommutative Geometry&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Nathan Hayford&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time/Location&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, September 23rd at 12:00pm, NES 102&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: Non-commutative geometry is a subject that grew out of the need to extend results about commutative Banach algebras to the non-commutative setting. It was pioneered by Alain Connes and his collaborators, and has since found applications in many areas of mathematics and physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this talk, we provide a gentle introduction to non-commutative geometry by studying one the simplest instances of it—the non-commutative torus. We compare the results of our calculations to what happens in the commutative case. Further, we demonstrate how the problem connects to the quantum mechanics of 2D electrons in an external magnetic field, and how this connection allows us to derive (formally) an old and famous result due to P. Levy on the area distribution of random walks in two dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algebraic Curves Over Finite Fields: Theory and Applications</title>
      <link>/talk/algebraiccurvesvincenzo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2022 03:27:45 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/algebraiccurvesvincenzo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Algebraic Curves over Finite Fields: Theory and Applications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Vincenzo Pallozzi Lavorante&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time/Location&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, September 16th at 12:00pm, NES 102&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: The study of algebraic curves defined over a finite field has attracted much
interest in recent times. The purpose of this talk is to introduce the basic notions
related to algebraic curves over finite fields, together with some examples of how it finds a concrete and common
application in different research areas. In particular we
will explore the connection with coding theory, permutation polynomials and see an
interesting application in finite geometry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digraph Homology to study DNA Rearrangement</title>
      <link>/talk/digraphhomology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 08:51:57 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/digraphhomology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Digraph Homology to study DNA Rearrangement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Lina Fajardo Gomez&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time/Location&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, September 9th at 12:00pm, NES 102&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: In this work, we introduce tools to study DNA recombination pathways and measure their complexity. Genome rearrangement in some ciliate species can be modeled by subword pattern deletions in &lt;em&gt;double-occurrence words&lt;/em&gt; (DOWs), words where each symbol appears exactly twice. The iterated deletions can be represented by a graph whose vertices are DOWs connected by an edge if one word can be obtained from the other through a pattern deletion. On this graph, called the ``word graph&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;, we build a complex comprised of cells defined by Cartesian products of simplicial digraphs where we define a boundary operator and compute homology groups. These topological invariants are used to analyze the word graphs of DOWs from data sets and to make comparisons between the genomes of three ciliate species as well as to describe DOWs whose graphs attain arbitrarily large Betti numbers.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Heilbronn Triangle Problem: History and Recent Developments</title>
      <link>/talk/heilbronntriangle/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Aug 2022 10:34:02 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/heilbronntriangle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: The Heilbronn Triangle Problem: History and Recent Developments&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Eion Mulrenin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time/Location&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday. September 2nd, at 2:00pm, NES 102&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: The Heilbronn triangle problem is an old problem in discrete geometry which seeks to maximize the value of
the smallest area of the triangles formed between triples of any set of n points in the unit square. More precisely, for
a configuration $D_n$ of $n$ points in $[0,1]^2$, set $\Delta(D_n)$ to be the smallest area of a triangle formed between any three
points of $D_n$. The Heilbronn problem then asks for the value of $\Delta(n) := \sup \Delta(D_n)$, where the supremum is taken over all
configurations $D_n$. We wish to present an overview of the interesting history of this problem, discuss some recent developments and results, and pose several related open problems and variants.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Harmonic Measure of a Slit Domain</title>
      <link>/posts/harmonic-measure/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2022 18:31:12 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/posts/harmonic-measure/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/HarmonicMeasure/HarmonicMeasure1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page01&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/HarmonicMeasure/HarmonicMeasure2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page02&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/HarmonicMeasure/HarmonicMeasure3.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page03&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/HarmonicMeasure/HarmonicMeasure4.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page04&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/HarmonicMeasure/HarmonicMeasure5.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page05&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/HarmonicMeasure/HarmonicMeasure6.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page06&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Differentiation in real topological vector spaces</title>
      <link>/talk/tvs_bryce/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2022 11:04:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/tvs_bryce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Differentiation in real topological vector spaces&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Bryce Virgin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, April 15th, at 2:00pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Tr2NVmJk1A4&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: Differentiation is a fundamental operation in the subject of analysis, which systematizes the process of approximating sufficiently regular functions and shapes with linear substitutes near points of interest. Many of the classical results of analysis deal with the properties of differentiation for maps between finite dimensional, Euclidean vector spaces, where the theory of differentiation is well-behaved. There is little difficulty in extending the concept of differentiation to quite general topological vector spaces, but in this case, derivatives will no longer act as expected. The talk will explore the generalization of the standard derivative to general real topological vector spaces, which important theorems and properties it retains from the Euclidean case, and which are lost in the generalization.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Extremal Graph Theory and the Problem of Zarankiewicz</title>
      <link>/talk/zarankiewiczeion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 17:21:01 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/zarankiewiczeion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Extremal Graph Theory and the Problem of Zarankiewicz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Eion Mulrenin&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, March 25th and April 1st, 12:30 pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1&lt;/strong&gt;:

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/OJ4ZehfJY54&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 2&lt;/strong&gt;:

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ellQWjn0QY4&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: Extremal Combinatorics is an area of mathematics which seeks to maximize properties of a structure given certain restrictions placed upon it. One goal of Extremal Graph Theory, then, as one might expect, is to find the maximum number of edges in a graph which does not contain a given subgraph. In this talk, we will introduce the subject by examining its origins in several classic theorems and by exploring several old and interesting open problems in the field, primarily the problem of Zarankiewicz. No background in graph theory or combinatorics will be assumed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introductory Lectures on Quantum Field Theory</title>
      <link>/talk/quantumfieldtheory/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jan 2022 10:53:52 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/quantumfieldtheory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Introductory Lectures on Quantum Field Theory&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Razvan Teodorescu&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, February 25th, 2:00pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lecture 1&lt;/strong&gt;:

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/EhsFLhbkVkI&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lecture 2&lt;/strong&gt;:

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nHAaP4UO9kA&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: Quantum field theory (QFT) is the mathematical formulation of our current theoretical description of nature&amp;rsquo;s fundamental laws. It relates deeply to functional analysis, operator theory, Lie groups representation theory, and PDE, and is known for open problems such as the 4D Yang-Mills Millenium problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The presentation will introduce the main elements of QFT by reviewing Einstein&amp;rsquo;s postulates of special relativity, irreducible representations of the Poincare group, the Pauli-Lubanski theorem and classification of free fields, Emmy Noether&amp;rsquo;s theorem, internal symmetry groups, minimal connections and gauge theory, leading to the derivation of the action functionals for electro-weak and QCD theories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The continuation would require a detour through Gaussian random field theory and the Feynman-Kac theorem, before returning via Wick calculus to QFT, &amp;rsquo;t Hooft-Veltman dimensional regularization, the Migdal-Kadanoff renormalization (semi)group and Feynman diagrammatic expansions for standard applications such as the Lamb precession, CPT theorem, asymptotic freedom and the Goldstone-Higgs theorem.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Statistical Mechanics and the Tutte Polynomial</title>
      <link>/talk/tutteising/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jan 2022 12:18:39 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/tutteising/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Statistical Mechanics and the Tutte Polynomial&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Nathan Hayford&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, January 28th, 2:00 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/x-LoRJ3UaX8&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: The Tutte polynomial is a well-known graph invariant, from which many important graph-theoretic properties
can be read off. We discuss the equivalence of this polynomial to an important model in statistical physics: the q-Potts
model, which is a generalization of the simplistic model of a magnet (the Ising model). We use this equivalence to
develop the well-known high-temperature expansion of the Potts model. Furthermore, we discuss what we can learn about graph theory from statistical mechanics, and vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Introduction to Coding Theory</title>
      <link>/talk/codingtheory/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2021 18:07:06 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/codingtheory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: An Introduction to Coding Theory&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Austin Dukes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, December 3rd, 2:00 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NULv-dp-UzQ&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: In this talk we will discuss the basic notions of coding theory. A
(linear) $[n, k, d]_q$ code C forms a vector space over $\mathbb{F}_q$, the finite field with q
elements, so we will begin by providing a brief overview of finite fields. Then
we will shed some light on the relationships among the parameters $n$, $k$, $d$ by
observing the singleton bound. Finally, if time permits, we will consider some
fundamental constructions of &lt;em&gt;maximum distance separable&lt;/em&gt; (MDS) codes, i.e.,
codes whose parameters achieve equality with respect to the singleton bound.
Audiences of all backgrounds are welcome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Brief Introduction to Lamplighter Groups and Diestel-Leader Graphs</title>
      <link>/talk/lamplighter/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Nov 2021 09:23:27 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/lamplighter/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: A Brief Introduction to Lamplighter Groups and Diestel-Leader Graphs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Austin Gaffglione&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, November 12th, 2:00 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Sl0TZMu7mo0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: In 1990, W. Woess proposed the following question: Is every &amp;ldquo;nice&amp;rdquo; infinite graph quasi-isometric to the Cayley graph of some finitely generated group? In 2001, R. Diestel and I.Leader conjectured that some of graphs in the family they defined were not quasi-isometric to the Cayley graph of any finitely generated group. This was later proven to be true in a 2012 paper by A. Eskin, D. Fisher, and K. Whyte. We will examine the general construction of a Lamplighter group and observe some of its algebraic properties. We will also develop the notion of a horocyclic product of two trees, which will define a subfamily of the Diestel-Leader graphs. In particular, we will focus on the graph DL(2) and show that it is isomorphic to the Cayley graph of the Lamplighter Group L2 with respect to a certain choice for the generating set.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced diffusivity and skewness of a diffusing tracer in the presence of an oscillating wall</title>
      <link>/talk/lingyunding/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Oct 2021 18:40:05 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/lingyunding/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Enhanced diffusivity and skewness of a diffusing tracer in the presence of an oscillating wall&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Lingyun Ding (University of North Carolina)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, November 5th, 2:00pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/N7fUZrqof7c&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: We develop a theory of enhanced diffusivity and skewness of the longitudinal distribution of a diffusing
tracer advected by a periodic time-varying shear flow in a straight channel. Although applicable to any type of solute
and fluid flow, we restrict the examples of our theory to the tracer advected by flows which are induced by a
periodically oscillating wall in a Newtonian fluid between two infinite parallel plates as well as flow in an infinitely
long duct. These wall motions produce the well-known Stokes layer shear solutions which are exact solutions of the
Navier–Stokes equations. With these, we first calculate the second Aris moment for all time and its long-time limiting
effective diffusivity as a function of the geometrical parameters, frequency, viscosity, and diffusivity. Using a new
formalism based upon the Helmholtz operator, we establish a new single series formula for the variance valid for all
time. We show that the viscous dominated limit results in a linear shear layer for which the effective diffusivity is
bounded with upper bound $\kappa (1+A^2/(2L^2))$, where $\kappa $ is the tracer diffusivity, A is the amplitude of
oscillation, and L is the gap thickness. Alternatively, for finite viscosities, we show that the enhanced diffusion is
unbounded, diverging in the high-frequency limit. Non-dimensionalization and physical arguments are given to explain
these striking differences. Asymptotics for the high-frequency behavior as well as the low viscosity limit are computed.
We present a study of the effective diffusivity surface as a function of the non-dimensional parameters which shows how
a maximum can exists for various parameter sweeps. Physical experiments are performed in water using particle tracking
velocimetry to quantitatively measure the fluid flow. Using fluorescein dye as the passive tracer, we document that the
theory is quantitatively accurate. Specifically, image analysis suggests that the distribution variance be measured
using the full width at half maximum statistic which is robust to noise. Further, we show that the scalar skewness is
zero for linear shear flows at all times, whereas for the nonlinear Stokes layer, exact analysis shows that the skewness
sign can be controlled through the phase of the oscillating wall. Further, for single-frequency wall modes, we establish
that the long-time skewness decays at the faster rate of $t^{-3/2}$ as compared with steady shear scalar skewness which decays at rate $t^{-1/2}$. These results are confirmed using Monte-Carlo simulations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Covid-19 Spreading: An Eigenvalue Viewpoint</title>
      <link>/talk/covid_alice/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Oct 2021 11:06:43 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/covid_alice/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Covid-19 Spreading: An Eigenvalue Viewpoint&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Haowei (Alice) Chen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, October 29th, 2:00pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3EouErwqbtk&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: How will a virus propagate? How long does it take to disinfect given infection rate and virus death rate? What is the best node to immunize? We answer these questions by developing a nonlinear dynamical system that models viral propagation in any arbitrary network and also a general epidemic threshold is proposed: the inverse of the largest eigenvalue of the adjacency matrix.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zeros of Harmonic Polynomials and Related Applications</title>
      <link>/talk/gravitationallensing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 09:10:26 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/gravitationallensing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Zeros of Harmonic Polynomials and Related Applications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Azizah Alrajhi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, October 22nd, 2:00 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/T9_wreuH_R8&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: In this thesis, we study topics related to harmonic functions, where
we are interested in the maximum number of solutions of a harmonic
polynomial equation and how it is related to gravitational lensing. In
Chapter 2, we studied the conditions that we have to have on the real
or complex coe cients of a polynomial p to get the maximum number
of distinct solutions for the equation $p(z) - \bar{z}^2 = 0$, where deg p = 2.
In Chapter 3, we discuss the lens equation when the lens is an ellipse, a
limacon, or a Neumann Oval. Also, we discuss a counterexample for a
conjecture by C. Beneteau and N. Hudson in [1]. We also in particular
discuss estimates related to the maximum number of solutions for the lens
equations for the Neumann Oval.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] C. Beneteau and N. Hudson. &lt;em&gt;A survey on the maximal number of solutions of equations related to gravitational lensing&lt;/em&gt;. Complex Analysis and
Dynamical System, Trends Math. Cham: Birkhauser/Springer, 23-38.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Continuum Limit of Theta Functions</title>
      <link>/talk/continuumthetafunctions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Oct 2021 12:11:31 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/continuumthetafunctions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: The Continuum Limit of Theta Functions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Fudong Wang (University of Central Florida)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, October 15th, 2:00pm-3:00pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/x75sjMwHzdw&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: The purpose of the talk is to introduce Venakides&amp;rsquo; 1989 CPAM XLII paper on the continuum limit of theta functions. The problem is closely related to the semiclassical limit (or small dispersion, or nonlinear WKB analysis) for the famous nonlinear PDE: Korteweg-de Vries equation. Theta function can be considered as high dimensional Fourier series. The continuum limit of theta function we will discuss is the limit when the size of the period matrix of the theta function goes infinite in a certain way (or one can say the genus of the corresponding Riemann surface goes infinite). And we will associate the leading behavior with a minimizing problem (variational problem).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Ito Calculus</title>
      <link>/talk/itocalculus/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Oct 2021 11:25:26 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/itocalculus/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Introduction to Ito Calculus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Nathan Hayford&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, October 8th, 2:00 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/iVeGX50a45s&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: The Ito calculus is at the foundation of the theory of stochastic PDEs. In this talk, I will introduce the calculus, and prove Ito’s lemma. I will then demonstrate how the theory of martingales + Ito’s lemma can be applied to derive deterministic equations for certain quantities appearing in the stochastic calculus. In particular, I will prove the conformal invariance of Brownian motion and the harmonic measure. If time permits, I will also start a discussion about Schramm-Loewner evolutions (SLEs).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Martingales and Stopping Times</title>
      <link>/talk/martingalesandstoppingtimes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Sep 2021 12:21:07 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/martingalesandstoppingtimes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Martingales and Stopping Times&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Zachary Forrest&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, September 24th, 2:00 pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part I&lt;/strong&gt;:

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/79dmo6O9PqE&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part II&lt;/strong&gt;:

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Y2OvW7mmLso&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: In Stochastic Calculus and elsewhere, the notion of Martingales and Stopping Times are invaluable for characterizing random processes whose mean behavior is invariant but whose data changes over time. In this talk we will clearly define the notions of Martingales, Stopping Times, and any necessary analytical objects; introduce basic properties of these objects, including Doob&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Optimal Sampling&amp;rdquo; Theorem; and briefly touch upon some applications of Martingales and Stopping Times in research.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drifting through random walks and Brownian motions</title>
      <link>/talk/brownianmotion/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Sep 2021 18:58:31 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/brownianmotion/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Drifting through random walks and Brownian motions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Nathan Hayford&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, September 17th&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 2:00pm-3:00pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/r8A-7IbNfBY&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;:  In this talk, we will leisurely wander through the area of study of random walks and Brownian motions. We will begin by studying many of the important properties and realizations of random walks. In particular, we will examine the return probabilities of random walks in 1, 2, and 3 dimensions; as more eloquently stated by S. Kakutani, “a drunk man will find his way home, but a drunk bird will be lost forever”. We will also study the scaling limit of a random walk, the so-called Brownian motion. Many of the properties of random walks will be reflected by Brownian motions, and we will see that they are the first example of a very important class of random processes known as martingales.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Random Matrix Theory</title>
      <link>/posts/randommatrices/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Aug 2021 18:24:20 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/posts/randommatrices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here, we discuss some selected topics and techniqes from random matrix theory. For sake of clarity, we will first
deal with 1-matrix models, and illustrate how they count the number of planar diagrams in a certain limit. Then, we
discuss the 2-matrix models, which enumerate 2-colored planar diagrams. For this, we will need the Harish-Chandra
(Itzykson-Zuber) formula, which we also derive. Before discussing the connections of these matrix models to enumeration
problems, we first derive some basic facts about the space of Hermitian matrices that we will eventually need in order
to perform calculations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will always let $\mathcal{H}$&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; denote the space of $n\times n$ Hermitian matrices, i.e. matrices $X$ such that
$X^\dagger = X$ (&amp;quot;$\dagger$&amp;quot; here denotes hermitian conjugate). The dimension of this space may be
computed by noticing the following: the hermiticity condition requires that the diagonal of the matrix be real
($z = \bar{z}$ implies that $z$ is real), therefore the diagonal entries contribute $n$ variables. Above the diagonal,
there are $2 \cdot \frac{n(n-1)}{2} = n (n-1)$ variables (the factor of two coming from real + imaginary components);
therefore we find the dimension of the space of Hermitian matrices to be
\begin{align}
\dim H_n = n + 2 \cdot \frac{n(n-1)}{2} = n^2.
\end{align}
It is often convenient for us to work in the so-called &lt;em&gt;eigenvalue variables&lt;/em&gt; on the space of Hermitian matrices.
These eigenvalues are of course real, by properties of Hermitian matrices; the remaining variables are variables in
the unitary group $U(n)/U_{diag}(n)$ and are called &lt;em&gt;angular variables&lt;/em&gt;. This is apparent, by writing
$X = U^\dagger \Lambda U$; note that replacing $U \to \text{diag}(e^{i\theta_1},\cdots e^{i\theta_n} )U$ does not change the representation.
Defining $du := dU^\dagger U = -du^{\dagger}$, we find that $dX$ takes the form
\begin{align*}
dX = d(U^\dagger \Lambda U) &amp;amp;= dU^\dagger \Lambda U+ U^\dagger d\Lambda U + U^\dagger \Lambda dU \\\
&amp;amp;= U^\dagger (d u^\dagger \Lambda + d \Lambda  + \Lambda d u) U \\\
&amp;amp;= U^\dagger (d \Lambda + [\Lambda, d u] ) U.
\end{align*}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The metric can then be computed as
\begin{align*}
g = \text{tr} (dX^\dagger dX) = \text{tr}(d \Lambda d \Lambda) + \text{tr}([\Lambda, d u])^2,
\end{align*}
which is diagonal in the coordinates $(d\lambda_i, du_{ij})$:
\begin{align*}
g = \sum_{i = 1}^n d\lambda_i^2 + 2 \sum_{i &amp;lt; j} (\lambda_i - \lambda_j)^2 (du_{ij})^2
\end{align*}
The volume form is then
\begin{align*}
d\text{vol}(X) 	&amp;amp;= \sqrt{\det g} \prod_{i=1}^n d\lambda_i \prod_{i &amp;lt; j} du_{ij}  \\\
&amp;amp;= 2^{n(n-1)} \prod(\lambda_i - \lambda_j)^2 \prod_{i=1}^n d\lambda_i \prod_{i &amp;lt; j} du_{ij} \\\
&amp;amp;\propto  dU \prod_{i &amp;lt; j}(\lambda_i - \lambda_j)^2 \prod_{i=1}^n d\lambda_i,
\end{align*}
where $dU$ is the Haar measure on $U(n)/U_{diag}(n)$. The quantity
\begin{equation}
V(\lambda) := \prod_{i &amp;lt; j}(\lambda_i - \lambda_j) = \det(\lambda_i^{j-1})
\end{equation}
is called the &lt;em&gt;Vandermonde determinant&lt;/em&gt;. We shall meet it often later. The exponent of two in the Vandermonde determinant
comes from the fact that there are twice as many variables $du_{ij}$, with contributions coming from real and
imaginary parts, respectively. Because it is a quantity we will need later, we also compute the Laplace-Beltrami operator on the submanifold
of the eigenvalue coordinates; this is
\begin{align*}
\Delta_{LB} &amp;amp;= \sum_{i=1}^n \frac{\partial^2}{\partial X_{ii}^2} + \frac{1}{2}\sum_{i &amp;lt; j}\left(\frac{\partial^2}{\partial \text{Re}(X_{ij})^2} +
\frac{\partial^2}{\partial \text{Im}(X_{ij})^2}\right)\\\ &amp;amp;=
\frac{1}{V^2(\lambda)}\sum_{i=1}^n\frac{\partial}{\partial \lambda_i} \left(V^2(\lambda)
\frac{\partial}{\partial \lambda_i} \cdot\right) + (\Delta \textit{ on the angular coordinates}),
\end{align*}
i.e., on only the eigenvalue coordinates, we have
\begin{equation}\label{eigenvalue-laplacian}
\Delta_{eigenvalues} = \frac{1}{V^2(\lambda)}\sum_{i=1}^n\frac{\partial}{\partial \lambda_i} \left(V^2(\lambda) \frac{\partial}{\partial \lambda_i} \cdot\right).
\end{equation}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-the-gaussian-unitary-ensemble--planar-diagrams&#34;&gt;$1$. The Gaussian Unitary Ensemble &amp;amp; Planar Diagrams.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now demonstrate how certain integrals over $\mathcal{H}$&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; can be related to enumeration of planar diagrams,
a fact which was first noticed by the physicists 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://projecteuclid.org/journals/communications-in-mathematical-physics/volume-59/issue-1/Planar-diagrams/cmp/1103901558.full&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;E. Brezin, C. Itzykson, G. Parisi, &amp;amp; J. B. Zuber&lt;/a&gt;.
Most of the results presented here are standard; they can be found in places like 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/math-ph/0406013&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt; by Phillipe Di
Francesco, or in 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.labri.fr/perso/zvonkin/Research/matrixint.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; by Alexander Zvonkin, for example.
Let $\mathcal{H}$&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; denote the space of $n\times n$ Hermitian matrices. We consider the measure
\begin{equation*}
d\mathbb{P}(X) = \frac{1}{Z_n} e^{-\frac{n}{2}\text{tr} X^2} dX,
\end{equation*}
where $dX$ is Haar measure on $\mathcal{H}$&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; (which we have just defined in the previous section), and $Z_n$ is a
normalization constant so that $\int d\mathbb{P} = 1$, called the \textit{partition function}. The ensemble of
such matrices, taken together with the probability measure $\mathbb{P}$&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;, form the &lt;em&gt;Gaussian Unitary Ensemble&lt;/em&gt; (GUE).
We denote the expected value of a random variable $f(X):$ $\mathcal{H}$&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; $\to \mathbb{R}$ in this ensemble by $\langle f(X) \rangle_n$; explicitly,
\begin{equation}
\langle f(X) \rangle_n = \frac{1}{Z_n} dX \int_{H_n} f(X) e^{-\frac{n}{2}\text{tr} X^2}.
\end{equation}
We wish to evaluate expected values of certain random variables in the large $n$ limit, in particular (Notice
that $X\in \mathcal{H}$&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; is dependent on $n$ as well; we suppress dependence to simplify notations.)
\begin{equation}
\langle \text{tr} X^k \rangle:= \lim_{n\to \infty} \frac{1}{n}\langle \text{tr} X^k \rangle_n.
\end{equation}
We claim that
\begin{equation}
\langle \text{tr} X^k \rangle = C_k,
\end{equation}
where $C_k = \frac{1}{k+1}{2k \choose k}$ is the $k^{th}$ Catalan number. This will follow from some
combinatorial arguments. We begin by proving the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color:blue&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem 1.1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
Let $S\in \mathcal{H}_n$ be a fixed matrix. Then,
\begin{equation}
\langle e^{\text{tr} XS}\rangle_n = e^{\text{tr} S^2/2n}.
\end{equation}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Proof.&lt;/em&gt;
We have that
\begin{align*}
\langle e^{\text{tr} XS} \rangle_n &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{Z_n}\int_{H_n}dX e^{-\frac{n}{2}\text{tr} (X^2 -
\frac{2}{n} XS)}\\\ &amp;amp;=
e^{\text{tr} S^2/2n} \frac{1}{Z_n}\int_{H_n}dX e^{-\frac{n}{2}\text{tr} (X-S/n)^2} \\\
&amp;amp;=e^{\text{tr} S^2/2n} \frac{1}{Z_n}\int_{H_n}d(X-S/n)  e^{-\frac{n}{2}\text{tr} (X-S/n)^2}\\\
&amp;amp;= e^{\text{tr} S^2/2n} \frac{1}{Z_n}\int_{H_n}dX e^{-\frac{n}{2}\text{tr} (X)^2}
= e^{\text{tr} S^2/2n},
\end{align*}
where in the last step, we used the fact that $dX$ is translation invariant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt; $\square$ &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consequentially, we can compute any expected value of interest by differentiating $f(S) := e^{\text{tr} S^2/2n}$
with respect to $S$, and evaluating at $S=0$. For example,
\begin{align}
\langle X_{ij} \rangle_n = \frac{\partial f(S)}{\partial S_{ji}} \bigg|_{S=0},
\end{align}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and
\begin{align}
\langle X_{i_1j_1}X_{i_2j_2} \rangle_n = \frac{\partial^2 f(S)}{\partial S_{j_1i_1}\partial S_{j_2i_2}} \bigg|_{S=0}.
\end{align}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Explicitly, we have that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color:green&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lemma 1.1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
For any indices $i_1,j_1,i_2,j_2$,
\begin{equation}
\langle X_{i_1j_1} \rangle_n = 0, \qquad \qquad \langle X_{i_1j_1}X_{i_2j_2}\rangle_n = \frac{1}{n}
\delta_{i_1 j_2}\delta_{i_2 j_1}.
\end{equation}
&lt;em&gt;Proof.&lt;/em&gt;
Note that the exponent of $f(S)$ is $\frac{1}{2n}\text{tr} S^2 = \frac{1}{2n}\sum_{k,l} S_{kl}S_{lk}$, and
that
\begin{equation*}
\frac{\partial}{\partial S_{j_1 i_1}}\frac{1}{2n}\sum_{k,l} S_{kl}S_{lk} =
\frac{1}{2n}\sum_{k,l} \left(\delta_{k j_1}\delta_{l i_1} S_{lk} +
S_{kl}\delta_{l j_1}\delta_{k i_1}\right) = \frac{1}{n}S_{i_1 j_1}.
\end{equation*}
Therefore, by the chain rule,
\begin{align}
\langle X_{i_1j_1}\rangle_n = \frac{\partial}{\partial S_{j_1 i_1}}e^{\text{tr} S^2/2n}=\frac{1}{n}S_{i_1 j_1}e^{\text{tr} S^2/2n}\bigg|_{S=0} = 0.
\end{align}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, by the product rule,
\begin{align*}
\langle X_{i_1j_1}X_{i_2j_2} \rangle_n &amp;amp;= \frac{\partial}{\partial S_{j_2 i_2}}\frac{1}{n}S_{i_1 j_1}e^{\text{tr} S^2/2n}\bigg|&lt;em&gt;{S=0} \\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{n}\delta&lt;/em&gt;{i_1 j_2}\delta_{i_2 j_1}e^{\text{tr} S^2/2n}\bigg|&lt;em&gt;{S=0} + \frac{1}{n}S&lt;/em&gt;{i_1 j_1}S_{i_2 j_2}e^{\text{tr} S^2/2n}\bigg|&lt;em&gt;{S=0}\\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{n}\delta&lt;/em&gt;{i_1 j_2}\delta_{i_2 j_1}.
\end{align*}&lt;/p&gt;
 &lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt; $\square$ &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, any &amp;ldquo;higher&amp;rdquo; expected value can be computed via &lt;em&gt;Wick&amp;rsquo;s theorem}:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color:blue&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem 1.2.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;em&gt;(Wick&amp;rsquo;s Theorem.)&lt;/em&gt; Let $I = {(i_1,j_1),\cdots (i_{2M},j_{2M})}$ be a collection of indices,
$1 \leq i_k,j_k \leq n$. Then,
\begin{equation}
\langle \prod_{(i,j) \in I}X_{ij} \rangle_n = \sum_{\pi \in \Pi_{2M}}
\prod_{(i,j),(k,l)\in \pi} \langle X_{i j}X_{k l}\rangle_n,
\end{equation}
where $\Pi_{2M}$ is the set of all &lt;em&gt;pairings&lt;/em&gt; of the index set $I$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, we have that
\begin{align*}
\langle X_{i_1 j_1} X_{i_2 j_2} X_{i_3 j_3} X_{i_4 j_4}\rangle_n &amp;amp;=
\langle X_{i_1 j_1} X_{i_2 j_2}\rangle_n \langle X_{i_3 j_3} X_{i_4 j_4}\rangle_n\\\
&amp;amp;+\langle X_{i_1 j_1} X_{i_3 j_3}\rangle_n \langle X_{i_2 j_2} X_{i_4 j_4}\rangle_n\\\
&amp;amp;+ \langle X_{i_1 j_1} X_{i_4 j_4}\rangle_n\langle X_{i_2 j_2} X_{i_3 j_3}\rangle_n.
\end{align*}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Proof.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;(Sketch.)&lt;/em&gt; The theorem follows from the fact that derivatives must come in pairs for nonzero
contributions to the expected value to appear; see the proof of the lemma. It is clear that the sum
must be taken over all such pairings. The full proof of this fact is given in 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.labri.fr/perso/zvonkin/Research/matrixint.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Zvonkin&amp;rsquo;s survey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt; $\square$ &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color:green&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Corollary 1.1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
The expected value of the product of an odd number of matrix elements is necessarily zero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using the above theorems, we are now able to compute expected values of quantities like $\langle \text{tr} X^k \rangle_n$. By
the corollary, we trivially have that $\langle \text{tr} X^{2k+1}\rangle_n = 0$; it remains to compute the traces of
even powers. This can be accomplished by realizing the pairings in Wick&amp;rsquo;s theorem as sums over families of $1$-
face maps. We briefly summarize these results. Let us begin by way of example. Consider the expected value
$\langle\text{tr} X^4 \rangle_n$; we have that, by linearity of $\langle \cdot \rangle_n$:
\begin{equation*}
\langle \text{tr} X^4 \rangle_n = \sum_{i_1, \cdots, i_4} \langle X_{i_1 i_2} X_{i_2 i_3} X_{i_3 i_4} X_{i_4 i_1} \rangle_n.
\end{equation*}
Using Wick&amp;rsquo;s theorem, we see that there are $3$ contributing terms in the above sum:
\begin{align*}
\langle X_{i_1 i_2} X_{i_2 i_3}\rangle_n &amp;amp;\langle X_{i_3 i_4} X_{i_4 i_1}\rangle_n,\quad
\langle X_{i_1 i_2} X_{i_3 i_4}\rangle_n \langle X_{i_2 i_3} X_{i_4 i_1}\rangle_n,\quad
\text{and }\\\ &amp;amp;\langle X_{i_1 i_2} X_{i_4 i_1}\rangle_n \langle X_{i_2 i_3} X_{i_3 i_4}\rangle_n.
\end{align*}
We will deal with each of these contributions separately. By Lemma 1.1, we see that the first term
is only nonvanishing if $i_1 = i_3$; this leaves three free indices, so that
\begin{equation} \label{termA}
\sum_{i_1, \cdots, i_4}\langle X_{i_1 i_2} X_{i_2 i_3}\rangle_n \langle X_{i_3 i_4} X_{i_4 i_1}\rangle_n
= \sum_{i_1, i_2, i_3} \frac{1}{n}\cdot\frac{1}{n} = n.
\end{equation}
Again by Lemma 1.1, we see that the second term
$\langle X_{i_1 i_2} X_{i_3 i_4}\rangle_n \langle X_{i_2 i_3} X_{i_4 i_1}\rangle_n$ is only nonvanishing
if $i_1 = i_2 = i_3 = i_4$, leaving only one free index, so that this term contributes a total factor of
$\frac{1}{n}$:
\begin{equation}\label{termB}
\sum_{i_1, \cdots, i_4}
\langle X_{i_1 i_2} X_{i_3 i_4}\rangle_n \langle X_{i_2 i_3} X_{i_4 i_1}\rangle_n =
\sum_{i_1} \frac{1}{n}\cdot\frac{1}{n} = \frac{1}{n}.
\end{equation}
Finally, the last term in the sum,
$\langle X_{i_1 i_2} X_{i_4 i_1}\rangle_n \langle X_{i_2 i_3} X_{i_3 i_4}\rangle_n$, similarly contributes
a factor of $n$, since the only constraint on indices here is $i_2 = i_4$, by the lemma:
\begin{equation}\label{termC}
\sum_{i_1, \cdots, i_4} \langle X_{i_1 i_2} X_{i_4 i_1}\rangle_n \langle X_{i_2 i_3} X_{i_3 i_4} \rangle_n
= n.
\end{equation}
Combining the results above, we find that
\begin{equation}
\frac{1}{n}\langle X^4 \rangle_n = \frac{1}{n}\left(n + \frac{1}{n} + n\right) = 2 +
\frac{1}{n^2};
\end{equation}
Thus, we can easily compute the large $n$ limit: $\lim_{n\to \infty}\frac{1}{n} \langle X^4\rangle_n = 2$, which is indeed
the second Catalan number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above computation is essentially generic; one computes $\langle X^{2k} \rangle_n$ by first applying Wick&amp;rsquo;s formula,
then computing the individual contributions of each pairing by investigating the number of free indices, and
finally by summing these contributions. In fact, the problem is essentially reduced to counting the number of
pairings that give only one free index, among the $(2k-1)!!$ possible pairings appearing in the sum. We can
count the number of such pairings using the following geometric interpretation of each of the terms.
Consider the Wick expansion of the trace $\langle\text{tr} X^{m}\rangle_n$; a generic term in this expansion will consist of
a product of &amp;ldquo;pair correlations&amp;rdquo;, i.e., expected values of pairs of matrix elements: $\langle X_{i j}X_{k l}\rangle_n$.
We draw a diagram with $n$ &amp;ldquo;half edges&amp;rdquo;, as seen here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/RandomMatrices_images/trX2n.png&#34; alt=&#34;Pair Correlations&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To each term in the Wick expansion of
$\langle \text{tr} X^{m} \rangle_n$, we associate one of these diagrams: if $(i_N,j_N)$ is paired $(i_M,j_M)$, we connect
the corresponding half-edges to form a full edge. The diagrams
can then be used to compute the contribution of each term in the expansion. For example, two possible pairings
appearing in the Wick expansion of $\langle\text{tr} X^6\rangle_n$ are depicted below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/RandomMatrices_images/trX6_terms.png&#34; alt=&#34;aathis is an image&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leftmost diagram corresponds to the term
$\langle X_{i_1 i_2}X_{i_2 i_3}\rangle_n \langle X_{i_3 i_4}X_{i_4 i_5}\rangle_n
\langle X_{i_5 i_6}X_{i_6 i_1} \rangle_n$; we see that this term is only nonvanishing when $i_1=i_3=i_5$, and for any
$i_2,i_4,i_6$. Thus, the diagram contributes a factor of $n$ to $\langle \textit{tr} X^6 \rangle_n$. On the other hand, the
diagram on the right corresponds to the pairing $\langle X_{i_1 i_2}X_{i_3 i_4}\rangle_n
\langle X_{i_2 i_3}X_{i_6 i_1}\rangle_n \langle X_{i_4 i_5}X_{i_6 i_6}\rangle_n$, which is only nonvanishing when
$i_1 = i_4 = i_6 = i_3 = i_2$, and for any $i_5$. It follows that this diagram contributes a
factor of $1/n$, which will vanish in the large $n$ limit, as the diagram is non-planar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we can conclude that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color:blue&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem 1.3.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
\begin{equation}
\langle\text{tr} X^{2k}\rangle_n = \sum_{g=0}^{[k/2]} \varepsilon_g(k) n^{1-2g},
\end{equation}
where $\varepsilon_g(k)$ is the number of labelled one-face maps with $k$ edges of genus $g$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular,
\begin{equation}
\frac{1}{n}\langle \text{tr} X^{2k}\rangle_n = \varepsilon_0(k) + o(1/n),
\end{equation}
where $\varepsilon_0(k)$ is the number of &lt;em&gt;planar&lt;/em&gt; labelled one-face maps with $k$ edges. For this reason,
the large $n$ limit is sometimes referred to as the &lt;em&gt;planar limit&lt;/em&gt;. It is well-known
that $\varepsilon_0(k) = C_k$, the $k^{th}$ Catalan number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-matrix-ensembles-and-orthogonal-polynomials&#34;&gt;$2.$ Matrix Ensembles and Orthogonal Polynomials.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most computations within the scheme matrix ensembles are performed with techniques from the theory of orthogonal polynomials. Let us illustrate this
connection in several different ways. Let us consider the Hermitian ensemble with measure
\begin{equation*} \label{V-ensemble}
d\mathbb{P}&lt;em&gt;n(X) = \frac{1}{Z_n} e^{-\text{tr} Q(X)} dX,
\end{equation*}
where $Q(X) = X^{2n} + \cdots$ is a monic polynomial of even degree. Along with this ensemble, we also consider the family of monic
orthogonal polynomials ${\pi_n(\lambda)}$, which satisfy the relation
\begin{equation}\label{Q-OP}
(\pi_m,\pi_n) := \int&lt;/em&gt;{\mathbb{R}}d\lambda e^{-Q(\lambda)} \pi_n(\lambda)\pi_m(\lambda)  = h_n \delta_{nm},
\end{equation}
where $V(\lambda)$ is the same polynomial, but in the real variable $\lambda$ instead of the matrix variable $X$. Our first connection between the
ensemble defined by the above measure and the polynomials ${\pi_n(\lambda)}$ is given by the following theorem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color:blue&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem 2.1.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
(Heine&amp;rsquo;s formula) The polynomials $\pi_n(x)$ satisfy
\begin{equation}
\pi_n(\lambda) = \langle \det(\lambda - X)\rangle_n.
\end{equation}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Proof.&lt;/em&gt;
The proof is rather straightforward; first, it is clear from its definition that the right hand side of the above equation
is a monic polynomial of degree $n$. Thus, we have only to show that this polynomial is orthogonal to $\lambda^m$, for
$0 \leq m \leq n$. Suppose this is the case; then,
\begin{align*}
Z_n \cdot \big(\lambda^m, \langle \det(\lambda - X)&lt;em&gt;n\big) &amp;amp;=
\int&lt;/em&gt;{\mathbb{R}} d\lambda  e^{-Q(\lambda)} \lambda^m\bigg[ \int_{\mathbb{R}^n}\prod_{i=1}^n d\lambda_i (\lambda - \lambda_i)e^{-Q(\lambda_i)}  V^2(\lambda_1,\cdots,\lambda_n) \bigg] ;
\end{align*}
Note that $V(\lambda_1,\cdots,\lambda_n)\prod_{i=1}^n(\lambda - \lambda_i) = V(\lambda_1,\cdots,\lambda_n,\lambda)$, the Vandermonde
determinant with one extra variable. Furthermore, the remaining piece of the integrand,  $V(\lambda_1,\cdots,\lambda_n)\lambda^m$, can be
rewritten as (labelling $\lambda = \lambda_{n+1}$):
\begin{equation*}
V(\lambda_1,\cdots,\lambda_n)\lambda^m = \frac{1}{n+1}\sum_{i=1}^{n+1} (-1)^{i+n+1} V(\lambda_1,\cdots, \hat{\lambda_i},\cdots,\lambda_{n+1})\lambda_i^m;
\end{equation*}
This is the expression for the determinant
\begin{equation*}
\begin{pmatrix}
1 &amp;amp; \lambda_1 &amp;amp; \cdots &amp;amp; \lambda_1^{n-1} &amp;amp;\lambda_1^m\\\
1 &amp;amp; \lambda_2 &amp;amp; \cdots &amp;amp; \lambda_2^{n-1} &amp;amp;\lambda_2^m\\\
\vdots &amp;amp; \vdots &amp;amp; \cdots &amp;amp; \ddots &amp;amp;\vdots\\\
1 &amp;amp; \lambda_{n+1} &amp;amp; \cdots &amp;amp; \lambda_{n+1}^{n-1} &amp;amp;\lambda_{n+1}^m\\\
\end{pmatrix};
\end{equation*}
Clearly, this expression vanishes if $m &amp;lt; n$, and so
$\det(\lambda - X)_n$ is orthogonal to the first $m$ monomials, and is thus the (unique) monic orthogonal polynomial, $\pi_n(\lambda)$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;text-align: right&#34;&gt; $\square$ &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the above proof, if $m=n$, by what we just argued, we have that
\begin{align*}
Z_n \cdot \big(\lambda^n, \langle \det(\lambda - X)&lt;em&gt;n\big)
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{n+1}\int&lt;/em&gt;{\mathbb{R}}d\lambda e^{-Q(\lambda)} \bigg[ \int_{\mathbb{R}^n}\prod_{i=1}^n d\lambda_i
e^{-Q(\lambda_i)}  V^2(\lambda_1,\cdots,\lambda_n,\lambda) \bigg] \\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{n+1} Z_{n+1};
\end{align*}
furthermore, since $\big(\lambda^n, \langle \det(\lambda - X)\rangle_n\big) = \big(\lambda^n, \pi_n\big) = (\pi_n, \pi_n) = h_n$, we obtain that
\begin{equation*}
Z_{n+1} = (n+1)h_n;
\end{equation*}
We therefore obtain inductively a second important link between orthogonal polynomials and matrix models:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color:blue&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem 2.2.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
The partition function of the matrix model defined above is related to the orthogonality constants ${h_k}$ by
\begin{equation}
Z_n = n! \prod_{k=0}^n h_k.
\end{equation}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wish to make one final connection between matrix models and orthogonal polynomials. Consider the probability density function on the
eigenvalues for this ensemble:
\begin{equation}
\rho_n(\lambda_1,\cdots, \lambda_n) :=  \frac{1}{Z_n} V^2(\lambda_1 ,\cdots,\lambda_n) e^{-\sum_{k=1}^n Q(\lambda_k)}.
\end{equation}
Recall that the Vandermonde determinant is the determinant of the matrix $\big(\lambda_i^{j-1} \big)$. Note that we can add any scalar
multiple of any row/column to any other row/column without changing the determinant; thus,
\begin{equation*}
\det \begin{pmatrix}
1 &amp;amp; \lambda_1 &amp;amp; \cdots &amp;amp; \lambda_1^{n-1}\\\
1 &amp;amp; \lambda_2 &amp;amp; \cdots &amp;amp; \lambda_2^{n-1}\\\
\vdots &amp;amp; \vdots &amp;amp; \ddots &amp;amp;\vdots\\\
1 &amp;amp; \lambda_{n} &amp;amp; \cdots &amp;amp; \lambda_{n}^{n-1}\\\
\end{pmatrix}
=
\det \begin{pmatrix}
p_0(\lambda_1) &amp;amp; p_1(\lambda_1) &amp;amp; \cdots &amp;amp; p_{n-1}(\lambda_1)\\\
p_0(\lambda_2) &amp;amp; p_1(\lambda_2) &amp;amp; \cdots &amp;amp; p_{n-1}(\lambda_2)\\\
\vdots &amp;amp; \vdots &amp;amp; \ddots &amp;amp;\vdots\\\
p_0(\lambda_n) &amp;amp; p_1(\lambda_n) &amp;amp; \cdots &amp;amp; p_{n-1}(\lambda_n)\\\
\end{pmatrix},
\end{equation*}
for any family of monic polynomials ${p_{k}(\lambda)}$. In particular, we will choose $p_{k}(\lambda) = \pi_k(\lambda)$,
the monic orthogonal polynomials with respect to the weight $e^{Q(\lambda)}$. Combining these two determinants, the density function becomes
\begin{align*}
\rho_n(\lambda_1,\cdots, \lambda_n) &amp;amp;=  \frac{1}{Z_n} \det(\pi_k(\lambda_i))\det(\pi_k(\lambda_j))
e^{-\sum_{k=1}^n Q(\lambda_k)}\\\
&amp;amp;=\frac{1}{n! \prod_{k=0}^n h_k} \det\bigg(\sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \pi_k(\lambda_i)\pi_k(\lambda_j)\bigg)
e^{-\sum_{k=0}^{n-1} Q(\lambda_k)}\\\
&amp;amp;=\frac{1}{n!} \det\bigg(\sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \frac{\pi_k(\lambda_i)\pi_k(\lambda_j)}{h_k}\bigg)e^{-\sum_{k=0}^{n-1}
Q(\lambda_k)}\\\
&amp;amp;=\frac{1}{n!} \det\bigg(\sum_{k=0}^{n-1}
\frac{\pi_k(\lambda_i)e^{-Q(\lambda_i)/2}\pi_k(\lambda_j)e^{-Q(\lambda_j)/2}}{h_k}\bigg)\\\
&amp;amp;:=\frac{1}{n!}\det(K(\lambda_i,\lambda_j)).
\end{align*}
The function
\begin{equation}
K(\lambda,\mu) := \sum_{k=0}^{n-1} \frac{\pi_k(\lambda)\pi_k(\mu)}{h_k}e^{-Q(\lambda)/2}e^{-Q(\mu)/2}
\end{equation}
is called the &lt;em&gt;Christoffel-Darboux&lt;/em&gt; kernel; it acts as a projector onto the span of the first $n$ orthogonal
polynomials, multiplied by $e^{Q/2}$. If $m &amp;lt; n$, integrating out the last $(n-m)$
variables, one finds that the joint density of the first $m$ eigenvalues is
\begin{equation}
\rho_n(\lambda_1,\cdots,\lambda_m) = \frac{(n-m)!}{n!} \det(K(\lambda_i,\lambda_j))_{i,j = 1}^m.
\end{equation}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-coulomb-gas-formalism&#34;&gt;$3.$ Coulomb Gas Formalism.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In random matrix theory, one is often interested in the large n (&lt;em&gt;planar&lt;/em&gt;) limit of certain quantities; by the
previous section, we are equivalently looking for asymptotic formulae for orthogonal polynomials. One technique
for addressing such questions is the coulomb gas method. For sake of clarity, we will focus our attention on one
particular object, and its asymptotics: the &lt;em&gt;free energy&lt;/em&gt;:
\begin{align*}
F = \frac{1}{n^2}\log Z_n = \frac{1}{n^2} \log \int_{\mathbb{R}^n} V(\lambda_1,\cdots,\lambda_n)
e^{-n\sum_{i=1}^nQ(\lambda_i)} d\lambda_1\cdots d\lambda_n.
\end{align*}
Moving the Vandermonde determinant into the exponent, we can rewrite the free energy as
\begin{align*}
\frac{1}{n^2} \log  \int_{\mathbb{R}^n} e^{-n^2 E(\lambda_1,\cdots,\lambda_n)}d\lambda_1\cdots d\lambda_n,
\end{align*}
where
\begin{equation}
E(\lambda_1,\cdots,\lambda_n) := \frac{1}{n^2}\sum_{i\neq j} \log \frac{1}{\lambda_i - \lambda_j} +
\frac{1}{n}\sum_{i=1}^n Q(\lambda_i).
\end{equation}
The above sum can be interpreted as an energy functional for a system of $n$ charges interacting via the $2D$ Coulomb
potential. The fact that the $\lambda_i&amp;rsquo;s$ are real translates to the condition that the charges are confined to live
on a wire (the real line). The charges all have mass $1/n$, and all have the same sign, and so the affect of the
coulomb interaction is repulsive. On the other hand, the charges sit in a background confining potential $Q(\lambda)$,
which holds them together. Note that both terms in $E(\lambda_1,\cdots,\lambda_n)$ are of order 1, by how we scaled
$Q\to nQ$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this interpetation in mind, let us turn our attention back to the free energy. When $n$ is very large, typical
saddle point analysis tells us that we expect the dominant contributions to the free energy to come from the minima of
$E$, i.e.
\begin{align*}
F &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{n^2} \log \int_{\mathbb{R}^n} e^{-n^2E(\lambda_1,\cdots\lambda_n)} d\lambda_1\cdots d\lambda_n\\\
&amp;amp;\sim \frac{1}{n^2} \log e^{-n^2 \min E(\lambda_1,\cdots\lambda_n)}\\\
&amp;amp;= \min E(\lambda_1,\cdots\lambda_n).
\end{align*}
Writing the density of charges as a measure $\mu = \frac{1}{n}\sum_{k=1}^n \delta_{{\lambda_{k}}}$, we can rewrite this
minimization problem as
\begin{align*}
\min E(\lambda_1,\cdots\lambda_n) &amp;amp;= \min \frac{1}{n^2}\sum_{i\neq j} \log \frac{1}{\lambda_i - \lambda_j} +
\frac{1}{n}\sum_{i=1}^n Q(\lambda_i)\\\
&amp;amp;= \min_{\mu(\mathbb{R}) = 1} \int\int \log\frac{1}{x-y} d\mu(x) d\mu(y) + \int Q(x) d\mu(x).
\end{align*}
As $n \to \infty$, we expect that the charges should coalesce into a continuous distribution of charge $\mu$, i.e.,
$ \frac{1}{n}\sum_{k=1}^n \delta_{{\lambda_{k}}} \to \rho(x) dx$, where $\rho$ has total charge $1$. This sort of
equilibrium problem is well-known in potential theory; we can use our physical intuition to try and find its
solution. In equilibrium, the effective potential (the potential coming from the charges themselves, plus the
external field) should be constant on the support of the charges, otherwise the charges would move around, and we
wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be in equilibrium. This yields the following equilibrium condition:
\begin{equation}
U^\mu(x) + Q(x) = \text{const.},
\end{equation}
for $x$ in the support of the charges. Here, $U^\mu(x)$ is the potential given off by the charges:
\begin{equation}
U^\mu(x) = \int \log\frac{1}{x-y} d\mu(y).
\end{equation}
Differentiating the equilibrium condition, we obtain the equation
\begin{equation}
C^\mu(x) + Q&amp;rsquo;(x) = 0,
\end{equation}
where $C^\mu(x)$ is the &lt;em&gt;Cauchy transform&lt;/em&gt; of the measure $\mu$:
\begin{equation}
C^\mu(x) = \int \frac{d\mu(y)}{y-x},
\end{equation}
considered here in the principal value sense. We are almost at our goal; all that remains is to recover the measure
$\mu$ from the above formula, and then plug it back in to the energy functional, and then we have our expression
for the dominant contribution to the free energy. But how do we recover a measure if we know its Cauchy transform?
Luckily, this question has already been answered for us; these are the famous Sokhotsky-Plemelj formulae:
\begin{align*}
\frac{d\mu(x)}{dx} &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{2\pi i}\bigg( C^\mu_+(x) - C^\mu_-(x)\bigg),\\\
P.V.\int \frac{d\mu(y)}{y-x} &amp;amp;= C^\mu_+(x) + C^\mu_-(x),
\end{align*}
for $x$ in the support of the charges. These formulae, along with a little knowledge of complex analysis, will allow
us to recover $d\mu(x) = \rho(x)dx$. Consider the function $P(z):=Q&amp;rsquo;(z)C^{\mu}(z) - (C^\mu(z))^2$. This function is
analytic everywhere in the complex plane, except possibly at the places where $C^\mu(z)$ loses analyticity&amp;ndash;the support
of the charges. Let us compute the jump of $P(z)$ across the support:
\begin{align*}
P_+(z) - P_-(z) &amp;amp;= Q&amp;rsquo;(z)\bigg(C^{\mu}&lt;em&gt;+(z)-C^{\mu}&lt;/em&gt;-(z)\bigg) - (C^\mu_+(z))^2 + (C^\mu_-(z))^2\\\
&amp;amp;= \bigg(C^{\mu}&lt;em&gt;+(z)+C^{\mu}&lt;/em&gt;-(z)\bigg)\bigg(C^{\mu}&lt;em&gt;+(z)-C^{\mu}&lt;/em&gt;-(z)\bigg)- (C^\mu_+(z))^2 + (C^\mu_-(z))^2\\\
&amp;amp;=0,
\end{align*}
and so $P(z)$ is continuous across the support of the charges, and thus continuous everywhere. By Morera&amp;rsquo;s theorem,
$P(z)$ is an entire function. Furthermore, we know the exact growth rate of $P(z)$ at infinity:
$P(z) = \mathcal{O}(z^{n-2})$, where $\deg Q = n$. Thus, by Liouville&amp;rsquo;s theorem, $P(z)$ &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a polynomial
of degree $n-2$. We thus have obtained an algebraic equation for $C^\mu(z)$:
\begin{equation}
(C^\mu(z))^2 - Q&amp;rsquo;(z)C^{\mu}(z) - P(z) = 0;
\end{equation}
this equation is quadratic in $C^\mu(z)$, and thus can be solved:
\begin{equation}
C^{\mu}(z) = -\frac{1}{2}Q&amp;rsquo;(z) \pm \frac{1}{2}\sqrt{Q&amp;rsquo;(z)^2 - 4P(z)
\end{equation}
Therefore, by the other half of the Sokhotsky-Plemelj formulae, we can recover the density:
\begin{equation}
\rho(x) = \frac{d\mu(x)}{dx} = \frac{1}{2\pi} \sqrt{4P(x) - Q&amp;rsquo;(x)^2}.
\end{equation}
In practice, computing the coefficients of $P(x)$ is not a trivial task, especially if the support of the measure is
more than one interval. However, if the potential $Q(x)$ is partiularly simple, the computations can be done rather
quickly; if $Q(x) = \frac{1}{2}x^2$, as it is for the GUE, then it is easy to see that $P(x) = 1$, and so the formula
above becomes
\begin{equation}
\rho(x) = \frac{1}{2\pi}\sqrt{4-x^2};
\end{equation}
this is &lt;em&gt;Wigner&amp;rsquo;s semicircle law&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-2-matrix-models&#34;&gt;$4.$ 2-Matrix Models.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now discuss $N$-matrix models, which are matrix models $n$ over copies of $\mathcal{H}$&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt;; for simplicity, we specialize to the case of $N = 2$.
We denote the matrices in the first copy of $\mathcal{H}$&lt;sub&gt;n&lt;/sub&gt; by $A$, and in the second copy by $B$. The probability measure we consider here is
\begin{equation*}
d\mathbb{P}&lt;em&gt;n(A,B) = \frac{1}{Z_n} \exp\bigg( -\frac{n}{2} \text{tr} (A^2 + B^2 + 2cAB)\bigg) dA dB.
\end{equation*}
The quantity in the exponent can be thought of as a quadratic form on pairs of Hermitian matrices $(A,B)$, with defining matrix
\begin{equation*} \label{quad-form}
\begin{pmatrix}
1 &amp;amp; c \\\
c &amp;amp; 1
\end{pmatrix}.
\end{equation*}
Expected values are denoted in the same way as before; this ensemble is also Gaussian in nature, and so the matrix version of Wick&amp;rsquo;s theorem
applies. As before, all one-point functions vanish identically. Thus, the relevant expected values to compute are the two-point functions; they are:
\begin{align*}
\langle A&lt;/em&gt;{i_1j_1}A_{i_2j_2}\rangle_n = \langle B_{i_1j_1}B_{i_2j_2}\rangle_n
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{n}\frac{1}{1-c^2} \delta_{i_1 j_2}\delta_{i_2 j_1},\\\
\langle A_{i_1j_1}B_{i_2j_2}\rangle_n &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{n}\frac{c}{1-c^2} \delta_{i_1 j_2}\delta_{i_2 j_1}.
\end{align*}
The computations are almost identical to the $1$-matrix case, and so we omit them here (the process involves the extra step of diagonalizing
the quadratic form above. The crucial point here is that the two point functions for &amp;ldquo;like&amp;rdquo; matrices are the same, and differ
from the two point function for the &amp;ldquo;mismatched&amp;rdquo; matrices by an overall constant. Therefore, the same sorts of combinatorial identites that
held before for the correlations now hold for graphs with two possible weights on the vertices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This connection of the 2-matrix model to enumeration of 2-colored graphs was exploited by V. Kazakov to answer questions
about the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/0375960186904330&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ising model on random planar graphs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;5-itzykson-zuber-integral-over-the-unitary-group&#34;&gt;$5.$ Itzykson-Zuber Integral over the Unitary Group.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this combinatorial interpretation of the model in mind, we would like to go about explicitly computing certain matrix integrals. To do this,
we will need to switch over to eigenvalue variables; this is not as trivial as a task as it was in the 1-matrix case. This is made apparent as
follows. Suppose we want to compute the expected value of some function $f(A,B) = f(\text{tr} A,\text{tr} B)$. This is written as
\begin{equation}
\langle f(A,B)  \rangle_n = \frac{1}{Z_n}\int_{A\in \mathcal{H}&lt;em&gt;n} \int&lt;/em&gt;{B \in \mathcal{H}&lt;em&gt;n}dA dB \exp\bigg( -\frac{n}{2}
\text{tr} (A^2 + B^2 + 2cAB)\bigg)  f(A,B).
\end{equation}
Letting $A = U^\dagger X U$, $B = V^\dagger Y V$, where $X = \text{diag}(x_1,\cdots,x_n)$, $Y = \text{diag}(y_1,\cdots,y_n)$ are diagonal matrices, we see that the above is
\begin{align*}
=&amp;amp; \frac{1}{Z_n}\int&lt;/em&gt;{X,Y\in \mathbb{R}^n} dX dY V(X)^2V(Y)^2f(X,Y) \exp\bigg( -\frac{n}{2} \text{tr} (X^2 + Y^2)\bigg)
\\\ &amp;amp;\times\int_{U,V \in U(n)/U_{diag}(n)} dU dV \exp\big(nc \text{tr} AB\big)
\end{align*}
We must pay careful attention to the integral
\begin{equation*}
\int_{U,V \in U(n)/U_{diag}(n)} dU dV \exp\big(nc \text{tr} AB\big) =  \int_{U,V \in U(n)/U_{diag}(n)} dU dV
\exp\big(nc \text{tr} U^\dagger X UV^\dagger Y V\big).
\end{equation*}
Making the change of variables in $V$: $W = UV^\dagger$, and integrating over $U$ first (and applying translation invariance of the Haar measure),
we see that the above integral becomes
\begin{equation}
\text{vol}(U(n)/U_{diag}(n)) \cdot \int_{W \in U(n)/U_{diag}(n)} dW \exp\big(nc \text{tr}  X W Y W^\dagger\big),
\end{equation}
where $X,Y$ are diagonal matrices, and $W$ is unitary. Integrals of this type are called &lt;em&gt;Harish-Chandra&lt;/em&gt; or
&lt;em&gt;Itzykson-Zuber&lt;/em&gt;
integrals over the unitary group. It turns out that such integrals can be computed explicitly. We will consider here a slight generalization of the
above:
\begin{equation}
I(A,B;s) := \int_{U(n)/U_{diag}(n)} dU \exp\big(s \text{tr}  A U B U^\dagger\big),
\end{equation}
where $A, B$ are Hermitian matrices. Our claim is the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;background-color:blue&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem 5.1.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
Let $I(A,B;s)$ be as defined above, and suppose $A$ has eigenvalues $a_1,\cdots, a_n$, and $B$ has eigenvalues $b_1,\cdots, b_n$. Then
\begin{equation}
I(A,B;s) = s^{-n(n-1)/2} \frac{\det(e^{a_ib_j})}{V(a) V(b)}.
\end{equation}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The remainder of this section is dedicated to a proof of this fact. We use the heat kernel technique, which is outlined
in 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/math-ph/0209019&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;a wonderful paper&lt;/a&gt; by P. Zinn-Justin and J.B. Zuber.
Consider the heat equation in the variable $A$:
\begin{equation}\label{heat-eq-1}
\begin{cases}
\left( \frac{\partial}{\partial t} - \frac{1}{2} \Delta_A \right) u(A,t) = 0,\\\
u(A,0) = f(A).
\end{cases}
\end{equation}
Here, $\Delta_A$ is the usual Laplace operator on $\mathcal{H}&lt;em&gt;n$:
\begin{equation*}
\Delta&lt;/em&gt;{A} = \sum_{i=1}^n \frac{\partial^2}{\partial A_{ii}^2} + \frac{1}{2}\sum_{i &amp;lt; j}\left(\frac{\partial^2}{\partial \text{Re}(A_{ij})^2} +
\frac{\partial^2}{\partial \text{Im}(A_{ij})^2}\right).
\end{equation*}
The heat kernel for this operator is easily derived (since $\mathcal{H}&lt;em&gt;n \cong \mathbb{R}^{n^2}$ in scaled coordinates):
\begin{equation*}
K(A,B;t) = \frac{1}{(2\pi t)^{n^2/2}}\exp\left(\frac{1}{2t} \text{tr}(A-B)^2\right);
\end{equation*}
The solution to the heat equation above is thus given by
\begin{equation*}
u(A,t) = \int&lt;/em&gt;{\mathcal{H}&lt;em&gt;n} dB f(B) \frac{1}{(2\pi t)^{n^2/2}}\exp\left(-\frac{1}{2t} \text{tr}(A-B)^2\right).
\end{equation*}
Let us suppose the initial data $f(A)$ depends only on the eigenvalue
variables, i.e. $f(A) = f(\text{tr}(A))$. Then, converting the above to eigenvalue variables $A = U^\dagger X U$, $B = V^\dagger Y V$, we find that
\begin{align*}\label{heat2}
u(A,t) = &amp;amp;\frac{1}{(2\pi t)^{n^2/2}}\int&lt;/em&gt;{\mathbb{R}^n} dY, V^2(Y)f(Y) \exp\left(-\frac{1}{2t} \text{tr}(X^2 + Y^2) \right)
\\\ &amp;amp;\times\int_{U(n)/U_{diag}(n)} dW \exp\big(\frac{1}{t} \text{tr} X W Y W^\dagger\big),
\end{align*}
where $W = UV^\dagger$. Note that the inner integral is the object we want to compute. Furthermore, the above formula implies that if
$f(U^\dagger X U) = f(X)$, then $u(U^\dagger X U,t) = u(X,t)$ for all $t &amp;gt; 0$ as well. Let us see examine the above equation in eigenvalue
coordinates. With the help of the formula we derived for the laplacian on the eigenvalue coordinates, we find that
\begin{align*}
0 &amp;amp;= \left( \frac{\partial}{\partial t} - \frac{1}{2} \Delta_A \right) u(A,t)
= \left( \frac{\partial}{\partial t} - \frac{1}{2} \Delta_{X} \right) u(X,t)\\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{\partial u }{\partial t} - \frac{1}{2}\frac{1}{V^2(X)}\sum_{i=1}^n\frac{\partial}{\partial x_i}
\left(V^2(X) \frac{\partial u}{\partial x_i} \right)\\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{\partial u }{\partial t} - \frac{1}{2}\frac{1}{V^2(X)}\sum_{i=1}^n \left(2V(X)\frac{\partial V}{\partial x_i}  \frac{\partial u}{\partial x_i}  + V^2(X) \frac{\partial^2 u}{\partial x_i^2}\right);
\end{align*}
Multiplying the above equation by the Vandermonde determinant $V(x)$, and using the fact that $\sum_{i=1}^n \frac{\partial^2 V}{\partial x_i^2}= 0$, the above equation becomes
\begin{align*}
0 &amp;amp;= \frac{\partial V u }{\partial t} - \frac{1}{2}\sum_{i=1}^n \left(2\frac{\partial V}{\partial x_i}
\frac{\partial u}{\partial x_i}  + V(X)\frac{\partial^2 u}{\partial x_i^2}\right)\\\
&amp;amp;= \frac{\partial V u }{\partial t} - \frac{1}{2}\sum_{i=1}^n \left(\underbrace{u\frac{\partial^2
V}{\partial x_i^2}}&lt;em&gt;{=0} + 2\frac{\partial V}{\partial x_i}  \frac{\partial u}{\partial x_i}  +
V(X)\frac{\partial^2 u}{\partial x_i^2}\right)\\\
&amp;amp;= \left(\frac{\partial}{\partial t} - \frac{1}{2} \sum&lt;/em&gt;{i=1}^n \frac{\partial^2}{\partial x_i^2}\right)V(X)u(X,t),
\end{align*}
and so $V(x)u(X,t)$ satisfies a heat equation of a different form. The generic solution for initial data $g(X)$ to the above heat equation is
\begin{equation*}
h(X,t) = \int_{Y\in \mathbb{R}^n} dY \frac{1}{(2\pi t)^{n/2}}\exp\left(-\frac{1}{2t}\text{tr}(X-Y)^2\right) g(Y);
\end{equation*}
In particular, for initial data $g(X) = V(X)f(X)$, we obtain the
formula
\begin{equation}\label{heat3}
V(X)u(X,t) = \int_{Y\in \mathbb{R}^n} dY \frac{1}{(2\pi t)^{n/2}}\exp\left(-\frac{1}{2t}\text{tr}(X-Y)^2\right) V(Y)f(Y)
\end{equation}
multiplying the previous equation by $V(X)$, we see that we have two expressions for the same function, $V(X)u(X,t)$. Equating these
expressions yields
\begin{align*}
&amp;amp;V(X)\frac{1}{(2\pi t)^{n^2/2}}\int_{\mathbb{R}^n} dY V^2(Y)f(Y) \exp\left(-\frac{1}{2t} \text{tr}(X^2 + Y^2) \right)
\int_{U(n)/U_{diag}(n)} dW \exp\big(\frac{1}{t} \text{tr} X W Y W^\dagger\big)\\\
&amp;amp;=  u(X,t)=\int_{Y\in \mathbb{R}^n} dY \frac{1}{(2\pi t)^{n/2}}\exp\left(-\frac{1}{2t}\text{tr}(X-Y)^2\right) V(Y)f(Y).
\end{align*}
Setting $f(Y) = \delta(Y-Y_0)$, we obtain that
\begin{align*}
&amp;amp;V(X)V^2(Y_0)\frac{1}{(2\pi t)^{n^2/2}}\exp\left(-\frac{1}{2t} \text{tr}(X^2 + Y_0^2) \right)
\int_{U(n)/U_{diag}(n)} dW \exp\big(\frac{1}{t} \text{tr} X W Y_0 W^\dagger\big)\\\
&amp;amp;=   \frac{1}{(2\pi t)^{n/2}}\exp\left(-\frac{1}{2t}\text{tr}(X-Y_0)^2\right) V(Y_0).
\end{align*}
Rearranging, and relabelling $Y_0 = Y$, we get
\begin{equation*}
\int_{U(n)/U_{diag}(n)} dW \exp\big(\frac{1}{t} \text{tr} X W Y W^\dagger\big) =
(2\pi t)^{-n(n-1)/2}\frac{\exp(\frac{1}{t}\text{tr} XY)}{V(Y) V(X)};
\end{equation*}
finally,
\begin{equation}
\int_{U(n)/U_{diag}(n)} dW \exp\big(\frac{1}{t} \text{tr} X W Y W^\dagger\big) =
(2\pi t)^{-n(n-1)/2}\frac{\det e^{\frac{1}{t}x_iy_j }}{V(Y) V(X)}.
\end{equation}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;6-2-matrix-models-and-biorthogonal-polynomials&#34;&gt;$6.$ 2-Matrix Models and Biorthogonal Polynomials.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as $1$-matrix models are connected to orthogonal polynomials, $2$-matrix models are connected to biorthogonal polynomials. Consider again
the $2$-matrix model defined by the measure
\begin{equation*}
d\mathbb{P}&lt;em&gt;n(A,B) = \frac{1}{Z_n} \exp\bigg( -\frac{n}{2} \text{tr} (A^2 + B^2 + 2cAB)\bigg) dA dB,
\end{equation*}
and recall that expected values of invariant functions $f(A,B) = f(\text{tr}(A),\text{tr}(B))$ are given by the formula
\begin{equation*}
\langle f(A,B)  \rangle_n = \frac{1}{Z_n}\int&lt;/em&gt;{A\in \mathcal{H}&lt;em&gt;n} \int&lt;/em&gt;{B \in \mathcal{H}&lt;em&gt;n}dA dB \exp\bigg( -\frac{n}{2}
\text{tr} (A^2 + B^2 + 2cAB)\bigg)  f(A,B).
\end{equation*}
Letting $A = U^\dagger X U$, $B = V^\dagger Y V$, where $X = \text{diag}(x_1,\cdots,x_n)$, $Y = \text{diag}(y_1,\cdots,y_n)$ are diagonal matrices, we
can integrate out eigenvalue variables to obtain
\begin{align*}
&amp;amp;= \frac{1}{Z_n&amp;rsquo;}\int&lt;/em&gt;{X,Y\in \mathbb{R}^n} dX dY V(X)^2V(Y)^2f(X,Y) \exp\bigg( -\frac{n}{2} \text{tr} (X^2 + Y^2)\bigg)
\\\ &amp;amp;\times\int_{U \in U(n)/U_{diag}(n)} dW \exp\big(nc \text{tr} XWYW^\dagger\big).
\end{align*}
The integral inside is precisely the Itzykson Zuber integral we computed previously; we insert the expression we derived for it into the
above formula, absorbing all constant factors into the partition function:
\begin{align*}
\langle f(A,B)  \rangle_n &amp;amp;= \frac{1}{Z_n&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;}\int_{X,Y\in \mathbb{R}^n} dX dY V(X)^2V(Y)^2f(X,Y) \exp\bigg(
-\frac{n}{2} \text{tr} (X^2 + Y^2)\bigg)
\frac{\det e^{nc x_iy_j }}{V(Y) V(X)}\\\
&amp;amp;=\frac{1}{Z_n&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;}\int_{X,Y\in \mathbb{R}^n} \prod_{k=1}^n dx_k dy_k f(x,y) V(x)V(y)\exp\bigg( -\frac{n}{2} \sum_{k=1} x_i^2  + y_i^2 + 2ncx_i y_i\bigg).
\end{align*}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thus, just as we were able to connect the 1-matrix model and orthogonal polynomials, we can connect the 2-matrix
to &lt;em&gt;bi-orthogonal polynomials&lt;/em&gt;; i.e., the polynomials $p_n(x),q_n(y)$ satisfying
\begin{align*}
\int_{\mathbb{R}} \int_{\mathbb{R}} p_n(x)q_n(y) e^{-\frac{n}{2}x^2-\frac{n}{2}y^2-2nxy} dxdy = h_n \delta_{nm}
\end{align*}
Of course, the same sorts of arguments can be made for more general potentials besides $x^2,y^2$; we postpone discussion
of this to a later entry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Probability Theory</title>
      <link>/talk/introprobability1-louis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Aug 2021 16:08:51 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/introprobability1-louis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Introduction to Probability Theory&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Louis Arenas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, September 3rd&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 2:00pm-3:00pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 1:&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pUfZzRKuXqM&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Part 2:&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BQkheSwlQhw&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: In this talk, we reinterpret the concepts from measure theory under the lens of probability theory. Using concrete examples, the aim is to introduce important concepts in probability theory and interpret their statistical meaning and connection to measure theory. This first talk aims to build an intuitive idea of the machinery used in probability theory to prove weak and strong law of large numbers, a theorem often taken for granted in applied statistics. In the second part we hope to motivate central limit theorem, and give a proof using characteristic functions. The target audience are students who have limited exposure to measure theory (statistics students), and students who are currently studying real analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Helton Howe Trace Formula</title>
      <link>/posts/the-helton-howe-trace-formula/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 15:19:15 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/posts/the-helton-howe-trace-formula/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/HeltonHowe/Helton_Howe-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page01&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/HeltonHowe/Helton_Howe-2.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page02&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working Differential Geometry</title>
      <link>/posts/working-differential-geometry/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 12:52:29 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/posts/working-differential-geometry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-01.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page01&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-02.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page02&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-03.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page03&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-04.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page04&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-05.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page05&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-06.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page06&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-07.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page07&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-08.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page08&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-09.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page09&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-10.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page10&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-11.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page11&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-12.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page12&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-13.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page13&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-14.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page14&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-15.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page15&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-16.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page16&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-17.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page17&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-18.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page18&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-19.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page19&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-20.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page20&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/WorkingDifferentialGeometry/WorkingDifferentialGeometry-21.png&#34; alt=&#34;Page21&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The trifecta of Hilbert spaces on the unit disc</title>
      <link>/talk/hilbert-spaces-on-the-disc/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 11:16:32 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/hilbert-spaces-on-the-disc/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1TB9cLz5Ja0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Hilbert spaces are common. Connection among them is rare. With this spirit, we will see the connection
among the three classical Hilbert spaces on the unit disc U. These Hilbert spaces are Hardy ($H^2(U)$), Dirichlet
($D^2(U)$) and lastly Bergman ($A^2(U)$). The idea comes from the intuition of evolving the remarkable identity called
as Littlewood Paley Identity for Bergman and Dirichlet spaces. During the presentation, audience will get to know more
about this identity. And also, the importance of this identity in the sense that how it relates to the Nevanlinna
Counting function. Nevanlinna Counting function $N_\phi(w)$ measures the &amp;lsquo;affinity&amp;rsquo; that $\phi$ has for value $w$ where
$\phi$ is a holomorphic map on $U$. Besides this, we will also see more connection among Hardy, Dirichlet and Riemann Zeta functions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Essentials of Viscosity Solutions in $R^n$</title>
      <link>/talk/the-essentials-of-viscosity-solutions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 16:11:32 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/the-essentials-of-viscosity-solutions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/0FRNeTc6Xyc&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/I_fsCAW3xrM&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/v3F4kv8f9v8&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; In their 1992 paper, authors Michael Crandall, Hitoshi Ishii, and Pierre-Louis Lions describe a class of solutions to certain 2nd order PDEs in R^n which they call &amp;ldquo;viscosity solutions&amp;rdquo;. In brief, a viscosity solution to an appropriate PDE is a continuous function possessing pointwise estimates for derivatives; they also possess a comparison principle which enables one to prove uniqueness of solutions to Dirichlet and Cauchy-Dirichlet problems. In this talk we will introduce the correct family of PDE for viscosity solutions; define viscosity solutions and prove their basic properties; discuss various results comparing viscosity and other notions of solutions; and, time permitting, we will also introduce a semicontinuous Perron&amp;rsquo;s method for existence of viscosity solutions and discuss parabolic viscosity solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A short Introduction to the Theta Functions</title>
      <link>/talk/introduction-to-theta-function/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Mar 2021 16:10:38 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/introduction-to-theta-function/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/cV9YMgCozsw&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory of theta function plays an important role in finding exact (quasi-) periodic solutions to the nonlinear PDEs. In this talk, we will introduce first the concepts of Riemann’s theta function (with characteristics) and Jacobi’s theta function. Then some of the simplest properties of those theta functions will be presented. If time permits, we will discuss a little bit about algebraic-geometry methods of constructing exact solution to KP equation.😄&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Methods of nonlinear equations in the theory of algebraic geometry</title>
      <link>/talk/riemann-schottky-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 13:50:43 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/riemann-schottky-problem/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/asVgNLcnAz0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Methods of nonlinear equations in the theory of algebraic geometry&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Nathan Hayford&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/time&lt;/strong&gt;: Wednesday, February 17th, 3:00pm-4:00pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;:
The Riemann-Schottky problem, in modern language, asks for a characterization of Jacobian varieties of among abelian varieties. From Riemann’s point of view, the question was to address the discrepancy between the 3g-3-dimensional space of moduli for compact Riemann surfaces of genus g from the g(g+1)/2-dimensional space of Siegel matrices, in which the space of Riemann surfaces embeds, via the period matrix. The problem remained open for almost a millennium. The first hint of a solution to this problem was found (somewhat surprisingly) by I. Krichever (1977), when he showed (more or less) that the period matrix for a Riemann surface could be used to construct tau functions for the KP hierarchy. S. Novikov conjectured that the converse also held, thus answering the Riemann-Schottky problem a la methods of integrable systems. This turned out to indeed be the case, with a proof from T. Shiota (1986) shortly thereafter. In this talk, I will attempt to fill in some of the details of this story, and explain some of the consequences of this theorem, both in integrable systems and algebraic geometry.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weyl&#39;s law and  hearing the area of a drum</title>
      <link>/talk/weyl-law-hear-area-drum/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2021 14:24:34 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/weyl-law-hear-area-drum/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/HiCA0n6x3Jo&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-nm5mjcNYDA&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Weyl&amp;rsquo;s law and hearing the area of a drum&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Louis Arenas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time&lt;/strong&gt;: Wednesday, February 3rd, 3:00pm-4:00pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;:
H. Lorentz in 1910 gave a series of lectures titled &amp;ldquo;Old and new problems in physics&amp;rdquo;. In the last lecture he mentions that J. Jean is interested in studying the growth rate of overtones of an electromagnetic wave in a bounded domain. He conjectures that the growth rate is independent of the shape of the domain and depends only on the volume and dimension of the domain. Herman Weyl, who was in attendance, precisely describes how fast these overtones grow two years after this lecture series. Since Weyl&amp;rsquo;s law holds for vibrating membranes, we start by describing the overtones of a drumhead via Dirichlet eigenvalues, compute the eigenvalues explicitly for a string with fixed ends, and build towards a proof of Weyl&amp;rsquo;s law in 2D for simply connected domains.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prodsimplicial and p-path complexes on directed graphs</title>
      <link>/talk/p-path-complexes-on-directed-graphs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 14:09:46 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/p-path-complexes-on-directed-graphs/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/9rlzTWD8o3o&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;:  Prodsimplicial and p-path complexes on directed graphs&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;:  Lina Fajardo Gomez&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date/Time&lt;/strong&gt;: Wednesday, January 20th, 2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: At face value, a graph is a simplicial complex that only has faces of dimension 0 (vertices) and 1 (edges). However, given appropriate definitions, higher dimensional cells can emerge. We present two such definitions, prodsimplicial complexes and p-path complexes, and compare in examples the homology groups obtained for different graphs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zoom Link&lt;/strong&gt;: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zoom.us/j/96345929862&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://zoom.us/j/96345929862&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Strong Asymptotics of Planar Orthogonal Polynomials: Gaussian Weight Perturbed by Point Charges</title>
      <link>/talk/asymptotic-op/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2020 13:22:22 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/asymptotic-op/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Strong Asymptotics of Planar Orthogonal Polynomials: Gaussian Weight Perturbed by Point Charges&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Meng Yang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/14SWXLKDks7bhNrO4tt3XrOQig0-uBWfD/view?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computing Reflection Coefficient of Schrondinger Operator via WKB method</title>
      <link>/posts/wkb-reflection/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 23:25:17 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/posts/wkb-reflection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;See the PDF:
&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34; src=&#34;/js/pdf-js/build/pdf.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;style&gt;
#the-canvas {
  border: 1px solid black;
  direction: ltr;
  width: 100%;
  height: auto;
}
#paginator{
    text-align: center;
    margin-bottom: 10px;
}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;div id=&#34;paginator&#34;&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;prev&#34;&gt;Previous&lt;/button&gt;
    &lt;button id=&#34;next&#34;&gt;Next&lt;/button&gt;
    &amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;
    &lt;span&gt;Page: &lt;span id=&#34;page_num&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt; / &lt;span id=&#34;page_count&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;embed-pdf-container&#34;&gt;
    &lt;canvas id=&#34;the-canvas&#34;&gt;&lt;/canvas&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script type=&#34;text/javascript&#34;&gt;
window.onload = function() {



var url = &#34;\/pdf\/wkb.pdf&#34;;


var pdfjsLib = window[&#39;pdfjs-dist/build/pdf&#39;];


pdfjsLib.GlobalWorkerOptions.workerSrc = &#39;/js/pdf-js/build/pdf.worker.js&#39;;


var pdfDoc = null,
    pageNum = 1,
    pageRendering = false,
    pageNumPending = null,
    scale = 3,
    canvas = document.getElementById(&#39;the-canvas&#39;),
    ctx = canvas.getContext(&#39;2d&#39;);



function renderPage(num) {
  pageRendering = true;
  
  pdfDoc.getPage(num).then(function(page) {
    var viewport = page.getViewport({scale: scale});
    canvas.height = viewport.height;
    canvas.width = viewport.width;

    
    var renderContext = {
      canvasContext: ctx,
      viewport: viewport
    };
    var renderTask = page.render(renderContext);

    
    renderTask.promise.then(function() {
      pageRendering = false;
      if (pageNumPending !== null) {
        
        renderPage(pageNumPending);
        pageNumPending = null;
      }
    });
  });

  
  document.getElementById(&#39;page_num&#39;).textContent = num;
}



function queueRenderPage(num) {
  if (pageRendering) {
    pageNumPending = num;
  } else {
    renderPage(num);
  }
}



function onPrevPage() {
  if (pageNum &lt;= 1) {
    return;
  }
  pageNum--;
  queueRenderPage(pageNum);
}
document.getElementById(&#39;prev&#39;).addEventListener(&#39;click&#39;, onPrevPage);



function onNextPage() {
  if (pageNum &gt;= pdfDoc.numPages) {
    return;
  }
  pageNum++;
  queueRenderPage(pageNum);
}
document.getElementById(&#39;next&#39;).addEventListener(&#39;click&#39;, onNextPage);



pdfjsLib.getDocument(url).promise.then(function(pdfDoc_) {
  pdfDoc = pdfDoc_;
  document.getElementById(&#39;page_count&#39;).textContent = pdfDoc.numPages;

  
  renderPage(pageNum);
});
}

&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fractional Calculus Approach for Flow Model in Porous Media</title>
      <link>/talk/fractional-calculus-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Nov 2020 23:12:31 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/fractional-calculus-approach/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Jb1eEDQBUPw&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Fractional Calculus Approach for Flow Model in Porous Media&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;
The Fractional Calculus approach is introduced into reservoir simulation. A three-dimensional relaxation model for viscoelastic fluid is built. The model based on the exact solution in Laplace space for some unsteady flow-Maxwell flow in an infinite reservoir  is obtained by Laplace transform and Fourier transform.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On solving the Dirichlet problem</title>
      <link>/talk/dirchlet-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 23:12:31 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/dirchlet-problem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Vu6MB6TQuns&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: On solving the Dirichlet problem&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Louis Arenas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;: October 23rd&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 11:00 pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: The talk will start by reviewing the mainstream strategies for solving the problem on simply connected domains, with particular attention to the disk. It is hoped that we have enough time to talk about Malmheden&amp;rsquo;s strategy for solving the problem on the disk. The talk should be of interest to anyone taking or wanting a review of basic concepts in complex analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Survey of Equilibrium in the Plane</title>
      <link>/talk/a-survey-of-equilibruim-in-the-plane/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2020 15:01:51 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/a-survey-of-equilibruim-in-the-plane/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Hye1gkDkCxU&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: A survey of equilibrium in the plane&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Nathan Hayford&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;: Friday, September 4th&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 11:00am&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract: Finding equilibria of charge distributions in the plane is a classical problem, which has found numerous applications in many other areas of mathematics and physics, including approximation theory, random matrices, quantum gravity, and integrable systems, among others. In this talk, I will survey some classical results from the theory of equilibrium distributions (using the language of potential theory), and provide some physical intuition for why such formulas hold. We will consider equilibrium with and without external fields. Furthermore, I will discuss some of the more modern applications of the subject; in particular, I will sketch how the equilibrium measures help us describe the asymptotics of certain families of orthogonal polynomials, as well how such problems appear in integrable systems, if time permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link to zoom meeting: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zoom.us/j/93365223865&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://zoom.us/j/93365223865&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt;: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Hye1gkDkCxU&amp;amp;t=2780s&amp;amp;ab_channel=USFGradMath&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Youtube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic Methods in Analysis</title>
      <link>/talk/asymptotic-methods-in-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2020 14:47:05 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/asymptotic-methods-in-analysis/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nDw2wLPQv3M&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Asymptotic Methods in Analysis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Fudong Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;: Thursday, 27th August.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 2:00 pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: In this talk, I will introduce the history of several well-known asymptotic methods in analysis. Then we will apply those methods via examples. The first example would be to apply Laplace&amp;rsquo;s method to get one of the oldest asymptotic results, the Stirling&amp;rsquo;s formula, i.e.
$$n!\sim e^{-n}n^n\sqrt{2\pi n},n\rightarrow \infty.$$ Next example is to apply the saddle point method to get the asymptotic of the integral
$$\int_{\mathbb{R}}f(z)e^{it(z^2+z)}dz,\quad t\rightarrow \infty .$$ Then I will introduce one recently developed asymptotic method called $\bar{\partial}-$steepest descent method, and apply it to study the long-time asymptotic for the linear Schrödinger equation:
$$
iu_t+u_{xx}=0,\quad
u(x,0)=q(x)\in H^1(\mathbb{R}).
$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;zoom&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zoom.us/j/98760291675&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Primes of the Form $p = x^2 &#43; ny^2$</title>
      <link>/talk/primes-of-the-form/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 10:44:14 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/primes-of-the-form/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/VBPrP4nChbo&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Primes of the form $p = x^2 + ny^2$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Louis Arenas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;: Thursday, August 6th&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 2:00pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: In a letter to Mersenne, dated 1640, Fermat formulated a problem asking for sufficient conditions to the titular primes in the case when $n=1,2,3.$ The first well known proof to the original problem (in the case for when $n=1$) was published by Euler in 1749, with the other two cases being completed in 1772. Naturally, Euler attempted to generalize the problem for arbitrary integers n &amp;gt; 0; while not producing any proofs, the ideas that Euler touched on would be expanded by Legendre, Gauss, and Lagrange. The goal for this talk is to outline a strategy that answers Fermat&amp;rsquo;s original problem along with a few more cases. If time permits, we&amp;rsquo;ll just mention a result that solves the general problem for countably many n integers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link to Zoom meeting: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zoom.us/j/98801740991&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://zoom.us/j/98801740991&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Video: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1iVpAtU8iRoVYILWLTB6MgfUe9ugrYsme/view?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Drive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Matroids</title>
      <link>/talk/introduction-to-matroids/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 22:36:21 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/introduction-to-matroids/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/SljIEkfzloA&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Introduction to matroids&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Lina Fajardo Gomez&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;: Thursday, July 30th&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 2:00pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: Matroids are mathematical objects that abstract the notion of linearly independent sets. They have applications in many areas of mathematics, ranging from combinatorics to field theory. In this talk I will give an overview of matroids, why they are studied and why I in particular took an interest in them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link to Zoom meeting: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zoom.us/j/93617336971&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://zoom.us/j/93617336971&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt;: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1V3Zg0KFIyk32S_mg2mMJ9I4lpIBchM70/view?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Drive&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slides&lt;/strong&gt;: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1tP9Qh3RJCplCVUsds1U9EBmmZd7hEZr0/view?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Drive&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Doing research as a student: tips and tricks</title>
      <link>/talk/doing-research-as-a-student/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 11:41:42 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/doing-research-as-a-student/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Doing research as a student: tips and tricks&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Giacomo Micheli&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;: Thursday, July 23rd&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 2:00pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract:
In this talk I will first explain how the publication process works. Then, I will go through some advice to do research as a student. In particular:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some of the methods I found most effective when I was doing independent research as a student.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;some general advice related to the process of submitting a paper to a journal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link to Zoom meeting: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zoom.us/j/95032330155&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://zoom.us/j/95032330155&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Gentle Introduction to Infinite-Dimensional Lie Algebras</title>
      <link>/talk/usf/infinite-lie-algebra/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 17:55:36 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/usf/infinite-lie-algebra/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/6789LcHqwP4&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: A Gentle Introduction to Infinite-Dimensional Lie Algebras&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Nathan Hayford&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;: Thursday, July 9th&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 2:00 pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: Infinite-dimensional Lie algebras have found applications in conformal field theory, integrable systems, and number theory, among other areas of mathematics. However, one wonders exactly how these algebras arise in such contexts, and moreover what is even meant by “infinite-dimensional Lie algebra” in the first place. In this talk, I will try to give a friendly introduction to the field of infinite-dimensional Lie algebras, and try to give the listener some operational familiarity with these structures by providing a few explicit examples. Furthermore, I will mention a few specific problems in mathematics where such algebras have been useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link to Zoom meeting: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zoom.us/j/5082038044?pwd=YUVBdkZvZU5RYXBYZmU5ZGRFZnE1Zz09&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://zoom.us/j/5082038044?pwd=YUVBdkZvZU5RYXBYZmU5ZGRFZnE1Zz09&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1by6zBTatZNO3CxFXer75CTtHR3hujoP5/view?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Drive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slides:&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1zPw8vC7dRtkJMMvsjc5SuMQeIlKBsUxV/view?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Drive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Nevanlinna-Pick Interpolation Problem</title>
      <link>/talk/nevanlinna-pick-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 13:37:03 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/nevanlinna-pick-problem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/C8-0k_UJnj8&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: The Nevanlinna-Pick Interpolation Problem&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: John Kyei&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;: Thursday, July 2nd&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 2:00pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;:
In this presentation, I will give an introductory discussion on the general Nevanlina-Pick Interpolation problem . Formulation of the Pick Problem and the nature of solutions to the Extremal Pick Problem. Subsequently, Nevalinna Formulation.
We will  also look at  the Finite Blaschke Products, Basic  analytic  and algebraic properties such as the characterizations of holomorphic functions on the disk, approximation and Differentiation of the Finite Blaschke Product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Link to Zoom Meeting: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zoom.us/j/99109270972&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://zoom.us/j/99109270972&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt;: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1_eVKFcjc5syRvp8s0CMusthbjAcX9EmX/view?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slides&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1wXFhZwWLGglGkBkSF67V9GKNmdav8GKb/view?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic Games for PDE</title>
      <link>/talk/usf/stochastic-games/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2020 22:58:12 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/usf/stochastic-games/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/TWf_XLzzUPI&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: Stochastic Games for PDE&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;: 2:00 pm, Thursday, June 25th, 2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Forrest, Zachary&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: This talk will serve as an introduction to techniques of stochastic games and their application to proving the existence of viscosity solutions to second order, degenerate-elliptic equations. We will define such equations and the class of viscosity solutions; give definitions and properties of martingales and stopping times, including Doob&amp;rsquo;s Optimal Sampling theorem; and give examples of stochastic games for Pucci&amp;rsquo;s maximal operators and the p-Laplace equation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1QlZqbhVYxEg6V5DHfCKCYfzpxzelyGXH/view?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Drive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slides&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1zSpf3r2OzizRkmCB7auiWQ5-fH9F1-81/view?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Drive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Brief Introduction to Differential Geometry and Minimal Surfaces</title>
      <link>/talk/minimal-surfaces/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jun 2020 14:54:17 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/minimal-surfaces/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/-FYXPfWy-bg&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: A Brief Introduction to Differential Geometry and Minimal Surfaces&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;: Thursday, June 18&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 2:00 pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Hayden Hunter (University of Florida)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Abstract: For this lecture we will be providing a small introduction to Differential Geometry including the definition of a regular surface, first and second Fundamental Forms, and Gauss and Mean Curvature. From here we shall move to describing what a minimal surface is as well as proving their existence and certain properties of minimal surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1h140EIRR51Ny9tkXAHYJQFapxTHXuPRb/view?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Google Drive&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Elementary Introduction to Fredholm Determinants</title>
      <link>/talk/fredholm-determinants/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 13:01:12 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/fredholm-determinants/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/m1CAUg0im4M&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title&lt;/strong&gt;: An Elementary Introduction to Fredholm Determinants&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker&lt;/strong&gt;: Fudong Wang&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date&lt;/strong&gt;: Thursday, June 11&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time&lt;/strong&gt;: 2:00 pm&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: At the beginning of the 20th century, Fredholm introduced a way to solve a class of linear integral equations which are now called them Fredholm integral equations. In his 1903&amp;rsquo;s paper, Fredholm introduced a determinant of a functional, which now is called Fredholm determinant. In this lecture, we will begin with the definition of determinant in the finite-dimensional spaces and review some properties of the determinants. After that, we will focus on the determinant of form $det(I+F)$ where $F$ is &amp;ldquo;small&amp;rdquo;. Following 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1ebU0SUTSXsVQclHXe9sNFJg3YZmiGmtF/view?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Fredholm&amp;rsquo;s 1903 paper&lt;/a&gt;, we will discuss Fredholm determinant $D_f$ and explore some properties of the determinant and how it connects to the finite determinants. Lastly, we will discuss how to construct the famous &amp;ldquo;soliton&amp;rdquo; solution to the equation of Koreteweg-de Vries by the so-called Fredholm determinant method introduced by Pöppe(1983).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video&lt;/strong&gt;: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1ghnW1hZSzLleX_UQ-t9g7BcbN1-RonFt/view?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;google drive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantum invariants of framed links from cohomology of self-distributive structures</title>
      <link>/talk/usf/quantum-invariants/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/usf/quantum-invariants/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Emanuele Zappala&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 2:00pm, Thursday, June 4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; In this talk I will give a brief introduction to knot theory and the notion of knot invariant. Next I will describe the process of algebraization of knot theory which naturally gives Yang-Baxter operators, Yetter-Drinfeld modules and racks/quandles etc. After recalling the definition of cohomology of racks, I will proceed to show how to construct an invariant of links and knotted surfaces from cocycles. I will therefore explain some recent joint works with M. Elhamdadi and M. Saito relating self-distributivity of higher arity structures and invariants of framed links, with a (categorical) perspective on how to realize them as quantum invariants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zoom links&lt;/strong&gt;: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://zoom.us/j/99982471312?pwd=Z0NTR2UraHZTQXI5TkdzNlM5K0FPUT09&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;click me.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Slides&lt;/strong&gt;: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1Pef6VJyfGRqouX5uf-QIy3oITf0NW85P/view?usp=sharing&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;google drive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Darboux Transformation and Soliton Equations </title>
      <link>/talk/usf/darboux-transformation-and-soliton-equations/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 20:47:23 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/usf/darboux-transformation-and-soliton-equations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Darboux transformation and soliton equations.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Yehui Huang (North China Electric Power University).&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, February $20^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 11:00am&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CIS 1045&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; In this talk, I will introduce a transformation originated
by Darboux in his study of the linear Sturm-Liouville problem. By
generalized Darboux transformations, I will present a solution formula
with multiple parameters for some soliton equations, including KdV and
NLS. After taking special choices for the seed solution and the
eigenfunctions, different types of exact solutions are derived, which
include solitons, breathers and rogue wave solutions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Calderón Problem</title>
      <link>/talk/usf/the-calderon-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2020 20:55:08 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/usf/the-calderon-problem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; The Calderón problem.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Lina Fajardo Gomez.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, February $13^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 11:00am&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CIS 1023&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; What do oil drilling and tumor detection have in common?
How could nonlinear equations be easier to work with? The Calderón
problem was first introduced as an inverse boundary value problem: how
information about the boundary of a domain can be used to determine
information about its interior. We will discuss the set up, some
applications, and a proposed solution for a class of Calderón type
inverse problems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variation Problem and How to Solve It</title>
      <link>/talk/usf/variation-problem-and-how-to-solve-it/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 21:02:58 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/usf/variation-problem-and-how-to-solve-it/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Variational Problems and How to Solve Them.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Nathan Hayford.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, February $6^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 11:00am&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CIS 1023&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Many problems in math and physics arise as problems of
extremizing some functional. Such problems include the isoperimetric
problem, minimal surface problem, and the formulation of Lagrangian
mechanics. We shall discuss the calculus of variations, and provide
worked out examples of how these techniques may be applied to solve such
problems. We will also discuss how such techniques may be applied to
write Lagrangian formulations of theories like electromagnetism and
general relativity, if time permits.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lorentz Group</title>
      <link>/talk/usf/lorentz-group/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2020 21:05:22 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/usf/lorentz-group/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Introduction to the Lorentz Group.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Louis Arenas.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, January $30^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 11:00am&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CIS 1023&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; The goal of this talk is to introduce the audience to the
definition of the Lorentz group and motivation in general relativity. We
will derive commutation relations, and if time permits show the
restricted Lorentz group is isomorphic to the Möbius group.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Riemann Hilbert Problem</title>
      <link>/talk/usf/riemann-hilbert-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2020 21:05:34 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/usf/riemann-hilbert-problem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Introduction to the Riemann-Hilbert Problem in $L^p$-space.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Fudong Wang.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, January $23^{rd}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 11:00am&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CIS 1023&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; We will first introduce some fundamental results about the
Cauchy operator. Base on the Cauchy operator, we will make it precise
what is the RHP and what is the solution to an RHP. Then we will talk
about the two types of inhomogeneous Riemann-Hilbert problems and
establish the equivalence between them. Finally, a uniqueness theorem of
RHP in $L^p$ will be given. If time permits, its application to the
inverse scattering theory will be mentioned too.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
