<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Grad Math@USF</title>
    <link>https://usfmath.github.io/</link>
    <description>Grad Math@USF</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://usfmath.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantum invariants of framed links from cohomology of self-distributive structures</title>
      <link>https://usfmath.github.io/posts/summer-talk-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://usfmath.github.io/posts/summer-talk-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Emanuele Zappala&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 2:00pm, Thursday, June 4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; In this talk I will give a brief introduction to knot theory and the notion of knot invariant. Next I will describe the process of algebraization of knot theory which naturally gives Yang-Baxter operators, Yetter-Drinfeld modules and racks/quandles etc. After recalling the definition of cohomology of racks, I will proceed to show how to construct an invariant of links and knotted surfaces from cocycles. I will therefore explain some recent joint works with M. Elhamdadi and M. Saito relating self-distributivity of higher arity structures and invariants of framed links, with a (categorical) perspective on how to realize them as quantum invariants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zoom links&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://zoom.us/j/99982471312?pwd=Z0NTR2UraHZTQXI5TkdzNlM5K0FPUT09&#34;&gt;click me.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://usfmath.github.io/archives/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://usfmath.github.io/archives/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Graduate Math Seminars at USF</title>
      <link>https://usfmath.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://usfmath.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Graduate Mathematics Seminar Series is a series of lectures hosted by (and for) graduate students in the mathematics department at USF. We hold weekly talks (for Summer 2020, Thursdays at 2pm, via Zoom), which are typically given by a graduate student from the department about their current area of research. The talks are meant to be accessible to graduate students, and serve as a means to promote discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several objectives this seminar has in mind, depending on the level of the graduate student. They are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beginning graduate students (first and early second year): The seminar serves as an introduction to the kinds of research the department has to offer, provided by fellow graduate students. Since the seminar is student-led, the environment better facilitates questions and discussions from students, and can be a good opportunity for newer graduate students to interact with other students in the department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More advanced graduate students: The seminar series acts as a place for advanced students to practice their communication skills, and prepare for upcoming conferences or talks in a more relaxed environment. Furthermore, it provides a place for students to discuss their research with their peers and possibly collaborate/exchange ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>