<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Grad Math@USF</title>
    <link>https://usfmath.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Grad Math@USF (Posts)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
    <atom:link href="https://usfmath.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title> [Talk] Quantum invariants of framed links from cohomology of self-distributive structures</title>
      <link>https://usfmath.github.io/posts/summer-talk-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://usfmath.github.io/posts/summer-talk-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Emanuele Zappala&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 2:00pm, Thursday, June 4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; In this talk I will give a brief introduction to knot theory and the notion of knot invariant. Next I will describe the process of algebraization of knot theory which naturally gives Yang-Baxter operators, Yetter-Drinfeld modules and racks/quandles etc. After recalling the definition of cohomology of racks, I will proceed to show how to construct an invariant of links and knotted surfaces from cocycles. I will therefore explain some recent joint works with M. Elhamdadi and M. Saito relating self-distributivity of higher arity structures and invariants of framed links, with a (categorical) perspective on how to realize them as quantum invariants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Zoom links&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&#34;https://zoom.us/j/99982471312?pwd=Z0NTR2UraHZTQXI5TkdzNlM5K0FPUT09&#34;&gt;click me.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Talk] Compressed Sensing</title>
      <link>https://usfmath.github.io/posts/compressed-sensing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2020 17:24:04 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://usfmath.github.io/posts/compressed-sensing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Compressed Sensing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Vasile Pop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, February 27th, 2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CIS 1045&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Compressed sensing (CS) is an exciting, rapidly growing
field that has attracted considerable attention in statistics, applied
mathematics, electrical engineering and computer science. CS offers a
framework for simultaneous sensing and compression of finite/infinite
dimensional vectors, that relies on linear dimensionality reduction. The
restricted isometry property (RIP) is at the center of important
developments in compressive sensing. In $\Bbb R^n$, RIP establishes the
success of sparse recovery via basis pursuit for measurement matrices
with small restricted isometry constants $\delta_{2s}&amp;lt;1/3$. A weaker
condition $\delta_{2s} &amp;lt; 0.6246$ is actually sufficient to guarantee
stable and robust recovery of all $s$-sparse vectors via
$l_1$-minimization. In Hilbert space a random linear map satisfies a
general RIP with high probability and allow recovering and extending
many known compressive sampling results. In this session, I provide a
comprehensive introduction to CS. This thesis extends the known
restricted isometric projection of sparse datasets in Euclidean spaces
$\mathbb{R}^N$ down into low-dimensional subspaces
$\mathbb{R}^k, k \ll N,$ to the case of low-dimensional varieties
$\mathcal{M} \subset \mathbb{R}^N,$ of codimension $N - k = \omega(N)$.
Applications to structured/hierarchical datasets are considered.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>[Talk] Darboux transformation and soliton equations</title>
      <link>https://usfmath.github.io/posts/darboux-transformation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Feb 2020 18:10:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://usfmath.github.io/posts/darboux-transformation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Darboux transformation and soliton equations.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Yehui Huang (North China Electric Power University).&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, February $20^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 11:00am&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CIS 1045&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; In this talk, I will introduce a transformation originated
by Darboux in his study of the linear Sturm-Liouville problem. By
generalized Darboux transformations, I will present a solution formula
with multiple parameters for some soliton equations, including KdV and
NLS. After taking special choices for the seed solution and the
eigenfunctions, different types of exact solutions are derived, which
include solitons, breathers and rogue wave solutions.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Old Talks IV</title>
      <link>https://usfmath.github.io/posts/old-talks-iv/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2020 18:37:13 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://usfmath.github.io/posts/old-talks-iv/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Modeling Physical Phenomenon: A derivation and exploration of
Laplacian growth.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Nathan Hayford.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, August $29^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 3:30pm&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 109&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Often the most interesting mathematical problems are
physically motivated: Laplacian growth is no exception. However, one may
wonder how such models are derived, i.e., what is their physical
relevance, what constitutes a good balance between an easily solvable
problem and a physically realistic one, among other questions. In this
talk, I plan on deriving Laplacian growth from first principles physics,
and explain the original motivations of the equation (in short, modeling
a 2D fluid domain&amp;rsquo;s expansion/retraction as fluid is pumped in/out from
above). I will briefly discuss the integrable structure of Laplacian
growth, and how it leads to exact solutions of the equation; finally, if
time permits, I will mention another modern application of Laplacian
growth in condensed matter theory: the integer quantum Hall effect.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Banach Algebra Approach to Wiener&amp;rsquo;s Theorem.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Raymond Centner.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, August $15^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 2:00pm&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 108&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; The Banach algebra setting can be very natural and useful
in harmonic analysis. In 1932, Norbert Wiener proved that the space of
absolutely convergent Fourier series is inverse closed, i.e., if f is a
non-vanishing continuous function on the circle with an absolutely
convergent Fourier series, then 1/f has an absolutely convergent Fourier
series. Roughly ten years later, Israel Gelfand proved this result using
the theory of Banach algebras. The purpose of this talk is to present
this theorem in the context of Banach algebras, shedding light on the
usefulness of abstraction in classical analysis.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; What is ... the inverse scattering transform?&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Fudong Wang.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, August $8^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 3:30pm&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 108&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; The story begins after the paper about a method for
solving the KdV equation by Gardner, Greene, Kruskal, and Miura (GGKM)
at 1967. That&amp;rsquo;s a first example of using IST to solve a nonlinear
integrable equation. In 1968, Lax found an operator way to generalize
GGKM&amp;rsquo;s method, which we now called &amp;ldquo;Lax pair&amp;rdquo;. In 1971, Zakharov and
Shabat use Lax&amp;rsquo;s method to solve the NLS equation. In 1974, Ablowitz,
Kaup, Newell, and Segur (AKNS) compare GGKM, Lax and ZS&amp;rsquo;s method in
nonlinear PDEs with the Fourier transform in the linear PDEs and the
term &amp;ldquo;inverse scattering transform&amp;rdquo; was born. In this talk, we will
briefly discuss how the inverse scattering transform works on solving
the NLS equation. If time allows, we will also talk about how to use IST
to generate the beautiful &amp;ldquo;soliton&amp;rdquo; wave solution.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; A Theorem of Radó Type for the &lt;code&gt;p&lt;/code&gt;-Laplace equation in the
Heisenberg group&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Zachary Forrest.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Wednesday, August $8^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 11:00am&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 108&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; It is known that in Euclidean spaces, the &lt;code&gt;p&lt;/code&gt;-Laplace
equation possesses a Radó-type result: That is, given a domain
$\Omega \subseteq \mathbb{R}^n$ and a fixed exponent
$1&amp;lt;\texttt{p}&amp;lt;\infty$, a function $u \in C^1(\Omega)$ which is a
viscosity solution to the $\texttt{p}$- Laplace equation
$$-\Delta_\texttt{p}u=0 ,,,, (1)$$ in the set is also viscosity
solution solution to Equation (1) in $\Omega$. This result was proven in
a paper (2005) of Juutinen and Lindqvist via the use of the Implicit
Function Theorem, and motivated by this approach and the works of
Franchi-Serapioni-Serra Cassano (2007) &amp;amp; Bieske (2006) we prove a
removability result for $\texttt{p}$-harmonic functions in the first
Heisenberg group $\mathbb{H}_1$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; A Survey of the Polynomial Method.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Austin Dukes.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, August $1^{st}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 3:30pm&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 13&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Recently, we have seen a surge of progress on many
long-standing problems from various fields using methods based on ...
polynomials? Based on relatively simple combinatorial arguments and
dimension-counting from linear algebra, these polynomial methods were
not initially perceived to be especially insightful. However, applying
polynomials has shed light on subtle yet essential structure in many
problems spanning many areas, and these methods are currently an
exciting and active area of research. In this talk, we will discuss the
Polynomial Method as well as give various examples of its use in fields
such as incidence geometry, harmonic analysis, and computer science.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Deep Learning.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Roshan Warman.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, July $25^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 3:30pm&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 13&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Deep Learning has received an increasing amount of
attention in recent years due to its break-through applications in many
fields. In this presentation, we present an exposition to the
intellectual enterprises of Neural Networks, building them ground up
from simple decision-making models, and provide an overview on basic
machine learning algorithms, with the eventual goal to discuss more
mathematically involved theorems and areas of research in statistical
learning theory. The only pre-requisites are basic foundations of
Analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Geometric group theory as a mathematical melting pot.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Lina Fajardo Gomez.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, July $18^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 3:30pm&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 13&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Geometric group theory is an area that studies discrete
groups through the connections between algebraic properties of the
groups and the topological and geometric properties of the spaces they
act on. It is a relatively new area of study that remains very active
(as demonstrated by the many conferences in the field and programs that
focus on it). This seminar talk is intended as a broad introduction to
geometric group theory, with examples of how it relates to different
areas of mathematics, and a motivation for its study.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Some fundamental formulas on the Cauchy-type integrals.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Fudong Wang.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, July $11^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 3:30pm&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 13&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; In the theory of boundary value problems of analytic
functions, Cauchy-type integrals play a fundamental role. There are
several fundamental formulas in the field, such like Sokhotsky-Plemelj
formula, Poincaré-Bertrand formula, Plemelj-Privalov theorem, and Marcel
Riesz&amp;rsquo;s inequality on the Hilbert transform. In this seminar talk, we
will start from the beginning to prove some of the mentioned theorems.
Those theorems are frequently applied in the theory of Riemann-Hilbert
problem, Random matrices and integrable systems.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Computing the Regulator of a Real Quadratic Order Using
p-Adic Methods.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Will Youmans.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, June $27^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 3:30pm&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 13&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; The regulator of a real quadratic order is defined as the
logarithm of the generator of the unit group (called the fundamental
unit). This value is closely tied to the class number and describes the
&amp;quot;density&amp;quot; of the units. The coefficients of the fundamental unit can
become very large, so rather than directly compute the regulator from
the fundamental unit itself we typically use a power product
representation of units derived from a generating set of relations for
the class group. Existing methods for computing the regulator from this
data suffer from a variable loss of precision which can be difficult to
control. We propose a p-adic method which simplifies the management of
the precision throughout the computation.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; What Can Random Matrices Do For You? &lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Nathan
Hayford.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, June $20^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 3:30pm&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 13&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Random matrix theory has been an indispensable tool for
mathematical physicists for the past few decades, but one may wonder how
relevant it is outside of this field. In this talk, I plan on explaining
the basics of random matrices, and how they have been used in fields
such as knot theory, graph combinatorics, number theory, biology,
quantum gravity, integrable systems, orthogonal polynomials, and... you
get the point. If time permits (and depending on the audience), I&amp;rsquo;ve
also prepared some more detailed examples of how random matrix theory is
used in each of these contexts. I&amp;rsquo;ll try and share as many of these as I
can in the allotted time.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; The presentation of the Braid group and faithfulness of its
Burau representation.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Louis Arenas.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, June $13^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 3:30pm&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 13&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; The talk will be centered on familiarizing the audience
with the geometric braid group and it&amp;rsquo;s presentation. From here, we will
see for a particular representation, for what parameters it will be
faithful.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Old Talks III</title>
      <link>https://usfmath.github.io/posts/old-talks-iii/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2020 18:31:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://usfmath.github.io/posts/old-talks-iii/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; An Introduction to Viscosity Solutions to the p-Laplace
Equation for Constant Exponent $1&amp;lt;\text{p}&amp;lt;\infty$.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Zachary Forrest.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Tuesday, October $1^{st}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 2:00pm&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 109&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; We explore Crandall, Ishii, and Lyon&amp;rsquo;s notion of solutions
in the viscosity sense for degenerate elliptic equations; after
preliminaries, we will focus on viscosity solutions for the equation
$$\label{Zach} \tag{$\star$}
-\Delta_{\text{p}} u := \text{div}\left( |\nabla u|^{\text{p} -2} \nabla u \right) = 0$$
posed in bounded domains $\Omega \subset \mathbb{R}^n$. Essential
properties of this family of solutions will be introduced, and we shall
also draw comparisons with the more classical notion of weak solutions.
Finally, we shall introduce Juutinen, Lindqvist, and Manfredi&amp;rsquo;s (2001)
result regarding the equivalence of weak and viscosity solutions to
Equation .&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; An Introduction to the Riemann-Hilbert Problems on the real
line.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Fudong Wang.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, September $26^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 2:00pm&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 109&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; In this talk, we will briefly discuss what is the
Riemann-Hilbert Problem(RHP). We will focus on the situation where the
contour is real line. Then formulate the RHP in $L^2$-space (hopefully).
The Sokhotski-Plemelj formula (or Cauchy operator) plays a fundamental
role in the theory of RHP, from where we can see the connection between
the singular integral equation and the RHP. A solution method, via the
Cauchy operator, will also be introduced (hopefully). Finally, we will
discuss how does RHP connect to the MKdV equation.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Rational Solutions to the Painlevé II equation.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Nathan Hayford.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, September $19^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 2:00pm&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 109&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; The Painlevé II (PII) equation appears in many problems in
theoretical physics, combinatorics, and random matrix theory. However,
being a non-linear equation, solutions can be difficult to construct.
One may wonder if there is a way to construct new solutions from old
ones, and in fact there is. We discuss the Bäcklund transformation
structure of PII with an explicit example: a family of rational
solutions to this equation.\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Connections between ladder operators and representation
theory (Part II)&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Louis Arenas.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, September $12^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 2:00pm&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 109&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Continuing the talk from last Thursday, using the
machinery developed last time; there will be an explicit connection to
spin states of a particle.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Old Talks II</title>
      <link>https://usfmath.github.io/posts/old-talks2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2020 18:28:55 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://usfmath.github.io/posts/old-talks2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Algebraic number theory and the ideal class group.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Will Youmans.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Tuesday, November $26^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 2:00pm&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 109&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Over three and a half centuries ago Fermat posed his
famous Last Theorem. Attempts to prove the theorem stimulated the
development of algebraic number theory throughout the $19^{th}$ century.
We will give an introduction to concepts in algebraic number theory from
a historical perspective with the aim of motivating the ideal class
group.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Euler&amp;rsquo;s $\zeta(2)$ and $\zeta(4)$ and other related series by
means of trigonometric integrals.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Cezar Lupu.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Tuesday, November $21^{st}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 2:00pm&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 109&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; In this talk, we shall illustrate how we can make use of
trigonometric integrals such as
$$\int_0^{\frac{\pi}{2}} \sin^n(x) dx, \quad \int_0^{\frac{\pi}{2}} \tan^n(x) dx$$
for derivation of Euler&amp;rsquo;s $\zeta(2)$ and $\zeta(4)$ formulas. On the
other hand, we also obtain Leibniz&amp;rsquo;s alternating series for $\log 2$ and
$\frac{\pi}{4}$.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Geometry, Links, and Magnetism.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Nathan Hayford.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, November $14^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 2:00pm&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 109&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; The linking number is a well-known invariant in topology,
and has been around since the time of Gauss. We will discuss this
invariant, and how it may be computed via purely geometric means.
Furthermore, we investigate Gauss&amp;rsquo; original motivations and intuition
for the linking number in the theory of magnetism. Finally, if time
permits, we mention how other topological invariants (like the Jones
polynomial) can be computed (in a surprisingly similar manner) via
appropriate topological field theories.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Rogue wave solutions to the nonlocal nonlinear Schrodinger
equation.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Rusuo Ye.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, October $17^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 2:00pm&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CMC 109&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; By using a matrix version of Darboux transformation with a
spectral matrix of the Jordan block form, rogue wave solutions to the
nonlocal nonlinear Schrödinger (NLS) equation are presented. General
rogue wave solutions up to the fourth-order are formulated. The
structure of these solutions is essentially determined by the
corresponding solutions of the Lyapunov equation. With appropriate
choices of free parameters, dynamics and distribution patterns for the
nonlocal NLS equation are shown to be much abundant than those for the
local NLS equation.\&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Old Talks I</title>
      <link>https://usfmath.github.io/posts/old-talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2020 18:20:34 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://usfmath.github.io/posts/old-talks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; The Calderón problem.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Lina Fajardo Gomez.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, February $13^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 11:00am&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CIS 1023&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; What do oil drilling and tumor detection have in common?
How could nonlinear equations be easier to work with? The Calderón
problem was first introduced as an inverse boundary value problem: how
information about the boundary of a domain can be used to determine
information about its interior. We will discuss the set up, some
applications, and a proposed solution for a class of Calderón type
inverse problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Variational Problems and How to Solve Them.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Nathan Hayford.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, February $6^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 11:00am&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CIS 1023&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Many problems in math and physics arise as problems of
extremizing some functional. Such problems include the isoperimetric
problem, minimal surface problem, and the formulation of Lagrangian
mechanics. We shall discuss the calculus of variations, and provide
worked out examples of how these techniques may be applied to solve such
problems. We will also discuss how such techniques may be applied to
write Lagrangian formulations of theories like electromagnetism and
general relativity, if time permits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Introduction to the Lorentz Group.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Louis Arenas.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, January $30^{th}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 11:00am&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CIS 1023&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; The goal of this talk is to introduce the audience to the
definition of the Lorentz group and motivation in general relativity. We
will derive commutation relations, and if time permits show the
restricted Lorentz group is isomorphic to the Möbius group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Title:&lt;/strong&gt; Introduction to the Riemann-Hilbert Problem in $L^p$-space.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Speaker:&lt;/strong&gt; Fudong Wang.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt; Thursday, January $23^{rd}$&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 11:00am&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; CIS 1023&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; We will first introduce some fundamental results about the
Cauchy operator. Base on the Cauchy operator, we will make it precise
what is the RHP and what is the solution to an RHP. Then we will talk
about the two types of inhomogeneous Riemann-Hilbert problems and
establish the equivalence between them. Finally, a uniqueness theorem of
RHP in $L^p$ will be given. If time permits, its application to the
inverse scattering theory will be mentioned too.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>